<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An embassage from heauen Wherein our Lord Sauiour Christ Iesus giueth to understand his iust indignation against al such, as being Catholikely minded, dare yeelde their presence to the rites and publike praier, of the malignant church, by Ralphe Buckham priest ...</title>
            <author>Buckland, Ralph, 1564-1611.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 145 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17128</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4007</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115956</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851173</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851173</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16437</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17128)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16437)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1541:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An embassage from heauen Wherein our Lord Sauiour Christ Iesus giueth to understand his iust indignation against al such, as being Catholikely minded, dare yeelde their presence to the rites and publike praier, of the malignant church, by Ralphe Buckham priest ...</title>
                  <author>Buckland, Ralph, 1564-1611.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 124 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed with licence [by the English secret press,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1611?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer from and publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Some pages marked.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16437:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16437:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>AN</hi> EMBASSAGE FROM HEAVEN.</p>
            <p>Wherein <hi>Our Lord and Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus giueth to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, his iuſt indignation againſt al ſuch, as being Catholike minded, dare yeelde their preſence to the rites and publike praier, of the malignant Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Raphe Buckland Prieſt.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t in nobis D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>en <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ciliationis pro Chriſto, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ue Legatiorie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, tanquam Deo exhorta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te per nos, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ciliamin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Deo.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </bibl>
               <p>God hath pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> conciliation, we be therof <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>; God as it were exhorting by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> for Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſake, be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Publiſhed with Licenſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:16437:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16437:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>AN</hi> EPISTLE TO AL Schiſmatikes.</head>
            <p>TO you, oh you miſerable, who ſtraying from the pathes of peace, runne as confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently forwards in darke and ſlippery wales, as if ye traced the ſteppes of truth and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, neither wandred one jot from the high way to ſaluation.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
            <p>WHo hath eares to heare, let him heare, a cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and a friendly admonition <hi>(gentle rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der)</hi> of that moſt mighty, and moſt humble Prince, who ſendeth this Embaſſage to prepare the harts of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſloyal ſubiects, to more perfect obſeruance of his lawes: which many inconſiderately, (becauſe they feare to heare them) doe violate; and feare to heare truly expounded, leaſt they ſhould vnderſtand them, and vnderſtanding them a-right, ſhould powerfully be moued to obey them, with loſſe of their reputation, life, and goodes. Which inconueniences (for ſo they eſteeme them) leaſt they might incurre: they ſtoppe their eares and wil not liſten to the voice of the wiſe enchaunter, telling them, that the Kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, is without compariſon of more value, then al the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> worldly pelfe: and that the troubles of theſe times,
<pb facs="tcp:16437:3"/> are not to be waighed in regard of the future glory, which ſhal be reuelled in them, euen in this life, through the teſtimony of a good conſcience, but chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the next, and euerlaſting life, by the perfect en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying of almighty God, and ſeing him there face to face as be is: to which beautifying viſion, by ſeruing God with a pure hart (for ſuch only ſhal ſee him) thou art earneſtly intreated by this booke (Godly reader) what euer thou art that haſt a ſoule to ſaue, rich, or poore, learned, or vnlearned, luke-warme Schiſmatike, or cold Catholike, for this worke concerneth you both, though with indifferency: in the peruſing whereof the more attention and heede thou doeſt beſtow, the better thou wilt accept <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the authours pious, and charitable indeauours; and reape vnto thy ſelfe great fruit to ſaluation, which whiles it is ripining in thee; ſhew thy ſelfe I pray thee, no leſſe grateful to the religious au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour hereof, by praying for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is ſoule, then to his yet ſuruiuing friend, at whoſe earneſt ſuite, this ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and profitable a meſſage is deliuered vnto thee, not without approbation and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile; after a careful view and examination of the ſame. <hi>Fare-wel.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16437:3"/>
            <head>AN EMBASSAGE FROM <hi>HEAVEN.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Earken ye erring ſoules,<note place="margin">1. The dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes.</note> who wil not enter the Arke, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for the ſafety of my Elect? yet hope to eſcape the vniuerſal floode of my wrath; who refuſe to leaue Sodome? yet feare not fire and brimſtone; who forſake not the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Chore? yet dread not to be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed of the earth; neglect to flie from Babylon, yet expect nothing leſſe then to be oppreſſed with the ruines thereof. Oh ye loſt ſheepe, who hauing receiued my marke, enter another ſold; yet wil needes be tearmed of my flocke, runne with the Theefe, and wil be holden inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent; partake in iniquity, yet wil be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted righteous; Ye broken branches ignorant of your owne decay; Ye that rent my vnſeamed coate, not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16437:4"/> a fault; teare my body without ſence of ſinne; breake the vnity of my Church vvithout ſcruple of Schiſme. Come forth before me and juſtifie your ſelues if ye can, cal together your wits, ſearch the depth of your harts, ponder the reaſons of your frailty, and the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of your defence, in equity I wil argue your offence, and contending by juſt judgement. I ſtand againſt you to your face: my Majeſty ſhal not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, to alleage what you can, I wil neither oppreſſe you with authority, nor ouer-rule without reaſon, but your owne guiltineſſe ſhal appale you, &amp; the cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of your crime, ſhal make you dumbe. Laying a-ſide the perſon of a Iudge, I the Creatour of al, referre the cauſe to the cenſure of al my creatures. To al both Angels and Men, I appeale to Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes and Heretikes; to Chriſtians and not Chriſtians, to your owne conſciences if ye haue any.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes no true ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of God.</note>I haue tried you and found you faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, I haue giuen occaſion of manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting your fidelity, and found you a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyal
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16437:4"/> generation; I haue prouided for you a plentiful harueſt of glorious and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal merits, I proffer the purchaſe of the Kingdome of heauen; but I perceiue you ſet at naught my wiſdome and bounty, contemning the treaſures of my King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as not worthy the vile price of temporal detriment. I haue proued you at the touch-ſtone, and diſcerned you to be b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe: I haue weighed you, and found you to light. Oh ſeede of Samaria, and not of Iuda, I hate your diſſimulation, I deteſt your cowardize, and abhorre your blindneſſe; my ſoule loatheth your hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting harts. Great is my indignation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, and digeſt your frowardneſſe I cannot.</p>
            <p>If any man with-hold your right,<note place="margin">3. Vngrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes and their inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God.</note> an action is ready, he is ſerued with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe and exclaimed againſt, for vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable dealing. How long ſhal I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde the intereſt vvhich I haue in your ſoules, and you giue no eare to my claime. You diſdaine to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned at your ſeruants handes, you brooke not diſobedience in your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16437:5"/> In caſe the fields and orchyeardes yeeld not their fruits, ye ſtorme and rage: But where is your owne duty? the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of your Maker, the loue of your Redeemer, the awe of your God? where are the fruits which my care haue deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued? Long haue I trauailed in manuring your barraine ſoules: I haue ſent my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers, who imploy their diligence, I haue by many occaſions ſollicited your harts, and with ſweet inſpirations, I haue at al times endeauoured to molliſie your obſtinate mindes. VVhat is that I ſhould doe to you and haue not done it? yet reape I nought but contempt, nor finde you other then ſtiffe and vntractable, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, and voide of al towardneſſe; Whatſoeuer you haue is of my beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence: your very life and being is of my bounty: neither dependeth your conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual preſeruation vpon any other aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, then the protection of my right hand. If al this be too little, I am ready to doe more, and greater matters I wil in your behoofe performe, then your ſelues would either haue expected, or deſired:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16437:5"/> and the good that I purpoſe toward you, in caſe you make your ſelues vvorthy thereof, cannot by mortal hart be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued. For which then of al my benefits doe you thus injury my patience? where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hath my gratious goodneſſe deſerued the contumely and reproch, vvhere-with your iniquity doth daily vexe me? Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and peruerſe people, yeeld you this thankes to my kindneſſe, this recompenſe to my deſerts? Why doe ye thus forſake me and deny me, diſpiſe and diſobey me, oppugne and aſſault me?</p>
            <p>Ye forſake me, and deny me,<note place="margin">4. Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiks deny, diſpiſe, &amp; impugne God.</note> and ſay with a bold countenance, wherein haue we forſaken and denied thee? Haue ye not renounced my ſeruice, caſt off my li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery, departed from my family, paſſed from my campe and coulers, to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries tentes, and yeelded to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of a Proteſtant? Ye diſpiſe and diſobey me, yet bluſh not to ſay, wherein (oh Lord) doe we diſpiſe or diſobey thee? Haue I not commanded you to loue me aboue al, and to confeſſe my name, my beleefe and Church, and to contend euen
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16437:6"/> vnto death for my truth ſake? Where is your loialty? Haue not I ordained Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for your ſpecial comfort, a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice celeſtial for memory of my excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding munificence, and as an homage of Chriſtian ſubjection? haue I not in my Church determinate ceremonies and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruances, for the greater dignity of my ſeruice, and abſoluter vnity of my fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? Al which ſithence you frequent not, where is your loue of me? or the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of my honour? you oppugne me alſo and aſſault me, and diſſemblingly ſay, wherein doe we oppugne and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault thee. Oh Sauiour? your exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple diſcomforteth others, vvhich would elſe doe wel, diſſolueth the courage, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth the number of my part, weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the cauſe of faith, and fortifieth the enimy.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5. Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them ſelues.</note>You flatter your ſelues notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding al theſe injuries, ſoothing your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences with a vaine pretence, that you loue and honour me ſtil, and with a falſe gloz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that you would not for a thouſand worldes forſake my ſeruice, nor deny my
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16437:6"/> ſacred name. How iniquity wil lie vnto it ſelfe, and beare the port of innocency? you liſt not found the depth of your owne hartes, for feare of touching the quicke, and eſpying the default, which you would not ſee, becauſe ſeing you would not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, and not amending muſt needes feele the continual fretting of a diſquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted conſcience, and thinke your ſoules to hang ouer the Dragons mouth. But I wil ſearch the ground of your hollow hartes; reueale your deepe diſſimulation, vnmaske your vaine pretences, and launce your feſtered ſoares to the very bottome.</p>
            <p>Doe ye not as <hi>Peter</hi> deny your ſelues,<note place="margin">6. By Peters denial is proued that Sch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſmatik deny Chriſt.</note> to be of my company? doe ye not appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly renounce, yea and ſometime abjure the fellowſhip of my followers? Doe ye not pretend to haue nothing to doe with their conuerſation, dreading to be pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, as one of their number? what is this but to diſclaime from my Religion, to depart from the corps of my vniuerſal Church, and to ſeperate your ſelues from the Congregation, vvhich among
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16437:7"/> al the people of this land, is al only left for my inheritance, and among whom only I am ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ued and honoured? To de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the communion of my flocke, is to deny me to be the true Sheep-heard, to renounce the fellowſhip of the houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of faith, is to renounce me for your Lord, and to diſauow my ſeruice. In not partaking with my children, you caſt me off as none of your Father, and in diſioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning your ſelues from the reſt of my mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, you giue ſufficient argument, that I am not your head. Thus you renounce me for your God, denying vtterly my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly name and Majeſty. If you be not vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to deny my God-head, no more was <hi>Peter:</hi> If you be not willed to reuolt in hart from your Redeemer, no more was he: If you be not expreſly commanded, to appoſtate from your faith and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, no more was he: If you deny with month <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o one article of beleefe, no more did he. In ſound beleefe of hart he paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed you farre (or if compariſon ſhould paſſe between<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you) I ſuppoſe you wil vaunt no prerogatiue. His zeale had in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16437:7"/> other reſpects beene often proued, as yours daily vpon ſmal trial, deſerueth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe. Your vvickedneſſe may almoſt juſtifie his weakeneſſe, at leaſtwiſe the enormity of your crime may extenuate the guilt of his frailty. Though he denied me his Maſter, by denying himſelfe to be a Diſciple, yet waded he not ſo farre, as by any other external ſigne, to beare ſhew of an enimy. Though he wickedly ſpake, and raſhly perjured as ouer-care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe what he replied, to a Girles queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Yet before the Magiſtrate at publike trial of his faith, he ſhewed more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, accompliſhing by loſſe of life, the period of this penance, then which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could he offer vp, nor I require any greater ſatisfaction. After thriſe offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, he conceiued harty and profound contrition, neither euer relapſed into like ſacrilege, but preſently bewailed vvith bitter teares, the grieuouſneſſe of his ſinne; and lamented the longeſt day of his life. The crowing of the Cocke was a peale to his penance, a memorial infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible to ſhowres of remorſe, and what
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16437:8"/> one day had committed of ſinne, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> daies following omitted not to ſobbe. How different are your deſerts from his? how contrary a courſe doe ye take? mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplying your ſinnes without al modeſty, if not without meaſure; not priuatly and ſodainly ſpeaking a word of Apoſtacy, but publikely in the face of the vvorld, committing actes of Hereſie, vvithful deliberation, with a hart reſolued to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard ſhipwracke, and giue aduenture vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſhelfes of ſinne. Not conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vvith eſchewing the exerciſe of the Catholike faith, and participation with the faithful, in profeſſion of conſcience; ye make no ſcruple to frequent the rites of a falſe beleefe, and partake vvith my vtter enimies, in the ſacrilegious impiety of their profeſſion. Yet whereas in him you acknowledge a damnable, and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal denial of me, the Lord of Hoſtes; your owne more apparant and odious, you wil not vnderſtand. But you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply (a crafty generation, as you are, crafty to deceiue your ſelues, and as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious in iniquity, as ſlow to piety)
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16437:8"/> you wil returne vpon me the reproofe of an vnjuſt complaint: ſaying,<note place="margin">7. Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes are not of the Catholike Church.</note> that you be Catholikes, and remaine firmely vnited to the Church my Spouſe.</p>
            <p>Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ye then ſay that Catholike Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantes, are not my proper ſtocke? Or can ye maintaine, that your ſelues are of their band, members of their Church and Fraternity? or vvil ye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouch that any company can be mine, vvhich imbraceth not wholy their faith? For vpon one of theſe three, of force ye muſt rely, if ye vvil juſtifie your ſelues, to be Children of my Church, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie your errour vvith hope of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Recuſants to ſtand vpon an aſſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed ground, none can juſtly deny,<note place="margin">8. The aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d where vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</note> or vvith reaſon cal their ſaluation in queſtion; vvho cleaue ſtedfaſtly to their fore-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers faith, departing neither on the right hand, nor on the left hand, from the rule of religion, but agonizing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto death in that Confeſſion, vvhere-unto their firſt chriſtined Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtours vvere conuerted, and wherein
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16437:9"/> al their Godly Predeceſſours, both ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly liued and happily died. Ye your ſelues, though ſlacke imitaters of their piety, cannot but admire it, and praiſe in them that perfect reſolution and heroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal courage, which bold affection though ye feele not, though in fits of remorſe, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſome time wiſh it. The very view, and regard whereof, might make you bluſh before men, and ſhal confound you at the ſupreame judgement.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">9. Recuſants highly to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for their zeale</note>Theſe are they vvhich nouriſh the ſparkes of that fire, which I came downe to kindle on earth: theſe only maintaine in this Realme my heauenly lampe, that it be not extinguiſhed, ſupport my law that it be not ruinated, glorifie my name that it be not vtterly defaced. Theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine like ſtarres in the darke night, like greene bayes in the midſt of hoary win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, like liuely freſh fountaines in the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy deſert. Theſe are they who liue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted, a-midſt a peruerſe generation, whoſe vertue ſtaieth my fury, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth my ſword from the reſt of the people. They walke in light, and know
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16437:9"/> what they doe, ye confeſſe them to doe beſt, and their vowed enimies acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge them to be in ſtate of ſaluation.</p>
            <p>With theſe you may wiſh to confort in conſcience,<note place="margin">10. Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes haue no part with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſants, neither are of the ſame Church.</note> to partake in profeſſion of faith: ye may in bare tearmes auouch as much, but ſhal neuer with reaſon be able to make it good. To become joynt-heires with them in the heauenly inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, ye may fooliſhly hope vpon raſh preſumption, but ſhal neuer attaine it for want of merit. Wil ye with them raigne, with whom ye doe not ſuſtaine? Wil ye deuide in the labourers hire, nor parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in his trauaile? Wil ye reape of their joyes, with whom ye ſow not in teares? Thinke ye to feaſt with them, in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Holy-day of the reſurrection, with whom ye faſt not the lent? Or beare a part in their Muſical <hi>Alleluia,</hi> which hold no voice in their tragical <hi>vah?</hi> in the Pſalmes not in the Threnes? Shal deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers be joyned with Confeſſors? diſclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers with Diſciples, fugitiues with fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, faithful Souldiers with falſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. Aſſoone ſhal ſhameleſſe Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taes
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16437:10"/> be enthronized with my holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, as peruerted Runnegates with my ſtedfaſt Recuſants; you deny your ſelues to be of their congregation before men; and ſhal I acknowledge you for one of them before my Angels? At the time of battaile you wil be none of them, and ſhal ye be found vncaſſered at the time of pay? Nay, nay, they which beare not my badge ſhal not be cladde with my liueri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s; they which be not of my retinew, ſhal not be fedde of my diſpenſe. What then? you are and wil be of my ſuite and ſeruice, as the beſt Catholikes are.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">11. Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes are not Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes.</note>And are you indeede? aske the Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, and he rejecteth you: aske the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutor, and he imbraceth you not: aske the Saints and Angels, and they abhorre you? I neuer yet tooke you for ſeruants of mine, ſince you caſt away my cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance, neither did I thinke that you durſt be ſo bold, as to aſcribe your ſelues to my family, who are retainers to another traine, and ſet your feete vnder my foes table. Are ye to be deemed of the true Church, making your reſort to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant?
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16437:10"/> may they be numbred in the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of the faithful, vvho are aſſociate with Infidels? How are ye of my flocke, who aſſemble in another fold, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch not to mine; feede of other pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures and forſake mine; heare the voice of other ſheepe-heardes, and diſobey mine? Haue no confidence in vaine lying wordes; ſay not in your hartes we be Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes: ye are none, you haue gone forth from among them, you haue ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated and diuided your ſelues, for feare of the world, refuſing to be partakers of their puniſhments and calamities, and to beare the yoke vnder vvhich they groane. Cal not your ſelues children of my Church, vaunt not to ſit in the lappe of my beautiful Spouſe. Ye are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like blacke a-moores Brats, and like Aegiptian Elues.</p>
            <p>Out of my ſight,<note place="margin">12. Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes ſhal receiue judgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes.</note> whom to behold is my griefe, the view of your vgly defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity I cannot abide. As I did to <hi>Chore</hi> and his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, ſo did I to al thoſe which negligently ſtaied among his Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; as I did to Samaria who had quite
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16437:11"/> caſt off my beleefe and law, and to her Idols, ſo d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d I to Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruſalem and her Idols, although ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e pretended no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolt from my ſeruice. And as in the day of vengeance, I wil plague Heretikes and Infidels, who manifeſtly rebelled againſt me, and impugned my faith, ſo wil I with the ſame Scorpions, ſcourge al thoſe who for feare of friendſhip (or what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect ſoeuer) adhere to their faction, and yeeld to their fury, al copartners in iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhal together haue their portion, in the lake burning with brimſtone, I am a jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous God, which wil not beare any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitor in intereſt of my inheritance, any riual in the loue of mans ſoule, nor indure that the reuerence due to my diuine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, be exhibited to any vngodly ſect, and the perſonal obſeruance, which my eſpouſed Queene challengeth, be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to an Adulterous Synagogue.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">13. Indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy.</note>No man can ſerue two Maſters, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſpleaſing the one, no man can warre vnder two aduerſary Princes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being a Traitour to the one. Mine you are by generation, by regeneration
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16437:11"/> more mine then before, by dependance of conſeruation, ye are more mine then your owne, yet wil you both in hart haue recourſe to me, and in act to <hi>Belzebub.</hi> You ſay you loue my Temple, but you enter into <hi>Bethel</hi> and <hi>Galgala:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos c. 5. verſ. 5.</note> like the Schiſmatical Iſraelites; you commend my Sac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i ice, but frequent the Calues of <hi>Hier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>boam.</hi> Ye pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tend to the Hil of Syon, but ye aſcend to adore in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Hil of Garazim as Samaritans, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming thereby companions of Diuels, and wounding th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conſciences of the weake, together with the true God,<note place="margin">4. Reg. 17.</note> ye adore the falſe. As thoſe libertines a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Corinthians,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 8. &amp; 10.</note> relying vpon your inward beleefe, ye freely eate of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous Sacrifices,<note place="margin">Apoc. 3.</note> as thoſe of Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cea, ye are neither hotte nor cold, and therefore loathſome to my ſtomacke. Ye reſemble thoſe which ſweare by God and by <hi>Melchom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aba. 1. v. 5.</note> vvhom therefore I threatned with vengeance, with wicked <hi>Achab</hi> ye worſhip God and Baal, nay your exteriour open worſhip, is whole to Baal, and not to me; you remaine with
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16437:12"/> me in fayned falſhood, and not in al your hart: nay rather you remaine with them, and on their ſide; if not in al your hart, yet in outward profeſſion; if not wilfully yet willingly; if not diſpitefully, yet diſobediently. Loue not me in word, but in worke; not with lips, but in hart; not in pretence, but in truth and ſincerity. The peruerſe, for faſhion ſake demanded <hi>what they ſhould doe to accompliſh my wil,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 18.</note> and when it was told them, neglected to fulfil it.</p>
            <p>If you be children of my Church, doe the workes of children; if you be my ſeruants, doe the vvorkes of ſeruants. Haue acceſſe to my Prieſts, frequent my Sacraments, cleanſe your ſoules by hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble confeſſion and penance, haue in due reuerence my rights and ceremonies, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour my ſeruice with your preſence, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate your ſelues before my holy Altar, lifting vp pure hartes and handes. Adore with zealous indeauour, at the houre of my dreadful Sacrifice; when propitiation for the liuing and dead, when memory of your Redeemer is celebrated. This
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16437:12"/> ſeeke through fire and vvater, through ſwordes and ſnares. Let neither diſtance of miles, nor friuoulous danger of places, nor ſurmiſed peril of your owne perſons impeach Godly indeauours, what ſhould I ſay more, declare by your deuotion, that you hunger and thirſt ſaluation, and that you ſet by nothing ſo much, as by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of your religion, and the preſence of me your Sauiour. Aboue al flie the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues of Sathan; flie al prophane praiers, al heretical co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenticles, al vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rites, al participation with any thing, that belongeth to the table and cuppe of Deuils. This doe, and then cal me <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of heauen, and the Church Mother of earth,</hi> I wil bleſſe you in life, and ſhee ſhal preſent you to meat your death.</p>
            <p>Here you ſtraine courteſie, here fleſh and bloud reclaimeth, the ſpirit taking the foile, and the old man triumphing;<note place="margin">14. Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> ſome of you diſcharge themſelues of their crimes, by myſtewards ouer rigorous au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity; and by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint of injury in being ſecluded from my ſacred miſteries? vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand ye what ye aske, oh ye hypocrites?
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16437:13"/> in this one thing only happy, that your ſuite is ſuſpended, and prudently rejected by thoſe which know, that they are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for diſpenſers, not for ſpenders and vvaſters of my celeſtial prouiſion, and that the childrens foode, is not to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to dogges, nor pearles to be caſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſwine, why demaunde ye that which would augment your damnation, which though moſt diuine, yet would no more ſanctifie you then it did <hi>Iudas,</hi> nor more preuaile you, then the Arke did profit the Philiſtian. The ſweeteſt conſerues in vndiſpoſed ſtomackes, turne to gal and choller; the moſt nouriſhing meates, breede moſt annoy in infected bodies, and nothing is wholſome, where wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth digeſtion. What flower or herbe the Spider feedeth on, turneth to venom, be it neuer ſo pleaſant; and vvhat Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents deuour, turneth to poiſon, be it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo wholſome.</p>
            <p>How dare you proffer to approch to my Altar, where ſo great a Majeſty is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, vvithout ſufficient examination and proofe of your worthineſſe? how can
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16437:13"/> ye be proued, vnleſſe ye be purged? how purged, but by penance? how admitted, to penance and pardon, either not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging your guilt, or not in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of amendment?</p>
            <p>Wel then,<note place="margin">15. Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiks are to be preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for Heretikes and why.</note> among my Catholikes ſince you are not, where ſhal I finde you? where are your raunges; being that you cleaue to Sectaries in actes of their Schi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmatical profeſſion, I pronounce you Proteſtants, whoſe proceedings in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture from the faith, though in priuate opinion (or poſſibly in talke) ye reproue, yet by preſence at their houſes of Idolatry you in appearance honour, by obeying you allow, by example you further, by deedes you confirme, by diſſembling you eſtabliſh. You goe thither as one of them, you ſit there as one of them, you behaue your ſelfe reuerently as one of them. The Caluiniſt taketh you for Proſelites, and as either conuerted or conformed; not altogether abhorring their pretended religion, not ouer reſolute in the old faith, and finally as perſons, not farre from their Kingdome. The poore Catholike ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalized
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16437:14"/> at your impiety, frameth no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conceipt, then that either you are quite peruerted to hereſie, or at leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that your faith is in the wane; that your Sunne is ſet, your deuotion done, the light of your ſoule extinguiſhed, that you are loſt ſheepe, diſtemblers, Schiſmatikes, and at the brinke of bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomeleſſe hereſie. And haue not thinke you the one and the other, juſt reaſon of their cenſure. You giue your hand, though you vvith-hold your hart; you weare the Deuils coate, though you cal him not Lord; you honour him, though you hate him; though you abhon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him, yet you obey him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">16. Thoſe which goe to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ticles of Heretical rites, are juſtly and properly called Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes.</note>Abhominable is Schiſme, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is the name of a Schiſmatike, but why ſhould this be a word of offence, to whom the ſubject thereof, and the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of ſo great a ſinne, is neither ſhame nor remorſe. Men are men, not priuy to the ſecre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of harts: the vnderſtanding cenſureth, as by the ſenſes is deliuered. The Church therefore judgeth, by that which ſhee ſeeth, not by that which ſhee
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16437:14"/> ſeeth not. The deede (as reaſon wil) doth prejudice the contrary word, and vpon the fact riſeth ſentence of faith?</p>
            <p>When my Church in her firſt prime, vvas nipped vvith ſharpe perſecution, ſo that diuers bloſſomes ſel from her branches, thoſe which through paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate feare condeſcended to Idolatry, vvere by the Bretheren condemned as fallen from their faith, rejected as A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtataes, and denounced excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, neither receiued againe vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out publike ſatisfaction, and many yeares penance.</p>
            <p>He that ſhould keepe the Saterday ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and pray with Iewes in their congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, were to be ſuppoſed a Iew: Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man would exclaime againſt the fact, vvithout caring for the cauſe. He that entreth any of <hi>Mahomets</hi> meſchits, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in his Temples, or kiſſeth the bookes of his law, is of euery Chriſtian man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for a Runnegate, and of the Turkes priuileged for a Boſerman; no man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring whether loue of their Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, or dread of extremity, whether carnal
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16437:15"/> ſenſuality and liberty of their law, or worldly proſperity, did moue him: fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their eies vpon his outward action, men let the intention repoſe it ſelfe in the proſound abiſme of the hart, what then ſhould hinder, why you alſo aſſociating Heretikes in their actions, yea principal and proper actions of their profeſſion, ſhould not be blazoned for a ſherents to Infidelity, bearing the blot of depa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ters from my Church Catholike, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of Schiſmatical perſons.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">17. Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts cannot be of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church, neither in their faith can be ſaluation.</note>I know, I know, what it is that lieth at your hart, a miſchiefe ſo corrupting your appetite, that it deſtreth not good, and your taſt that it diſcerneth not euil; a priuy poiſon, but ſo peſtiterous, ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numming (not the ſenſes, but the ſoule) that if it be not exhauſted, an incureable letargy, a mortal and euerlaſting ſleepe enſueth, ye are not perſwaded forſooth, that the Proteſtants religion is ſo abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable; they are to preciſe, which either make them Heretikes, or thinke that Heretikes muſt needes miſcarry. What? we be al Chriſtians, beleeue in one Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16437:15"/> expect one heauen, and enjoy one redemption. Haue not al men ſoules to ſaue: little diffe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ences make no great ſquare, in the foundation we agree. At leaſtwiſe, whatſoeuer their liues be wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and doctrine falſe, their praiers and Churches muſt needs be of God, becauſe they be good, and needes be good, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they honour God.</p>
            <p>Ah ingenious impiety, how thou tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and toſſeſt to winde from thy accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer? nay rather, ah fooliſh ſtubborne blindneſſe, which wil not ſee that, which is as cleare as noone day, which taketh for one (or as not much different) thoſe thinges which are as wide diſtant as the two poles of heauen. To take your ſelues for a particular Church, is vnpoſſible for a heedleſſe multitude, who haue neither Temple, Altar, Prieſt, nor Sacrifice, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſtict members, nor any band of vnion. Aſwel you may thinke of going at the latter day, neither to heauen nor to hel, as to thinke in this life of a Neutrali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? Blinde you are, if you perceiue not your ſelues to be ſeperated from my
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16437:16"/> Church; but if you imagine that thoſe whom you cleaue vnto, may be my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, and that in their praiers, holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; or in their faith, ſaluation may be found; then are ye both blinde and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 17.</note>Take heede what you ſay, to juſtifie the wicked is as deteſtable, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the juſt. Wil you diuide my Church, whoſe eſpecial marke and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty is vnity? or wil you giue me two Bodies miſtical, two Spouſes vnſpotted, two chaſt Turtles, two Citties on hilles, two Kingdomes, two Families, two Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of truth; Am I an adulterer, or am I deuorſed from my loue. To ſay that Proteſtants may by their profeſſion be ſaued, is either to make an other God beſide me, or to make me none; to make an other <hi>ſummum bonum,</hi> or to make me euil, to league me with <hi>Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer,</hi> or to make <hi>Iehonah Sathan,</hi> to conclude me as authour of diſſention, or patron of impiety, a double diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler, or a flat Heretike.</p>
            <p>If I can haue two Churches ſo diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16437:16"/> in rites, ſo contrary in doctrine, ſo naturally and neceſſarily tending the one to the vtter extirpation of the other, then giue me two heauens for them, and contrary glories for their oppoſite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts. Diuide my God-head vvith fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Manes,</hi> and defend one God good, and an other euil; or ſay that I am mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table good, and badde by enter-change of places, and enter-courſe of times. If there bee two Churches, prouide them of two Chriſtes; if there be two Moones, finde them two Sunnes: An other Sunne to lighten this other Moone; an other Chriſt to illuminate this other Church; an other Redeemer to waſh her in his bloud; an other Holy Ghoſt to Sanctifie her: for I dyed but for one, my diuine Spirit ſanctifieth but one.</p>
            <p>If on the other ſide,<note place="margin">18. The per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes and Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtants.</note> you joyne Calui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts with Catholikes in one Church, then ſet togither the Woolfe with the Lambe; couple the Lyon vvith the Hart; the Goſ-hawke vvith the Partridge, and they ſhal wel agree. No, no, heauen and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16437:17"/> hel haue as much affinity, as haue theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wo religions, and ſhal aſſoone ſhake handes, the one being ſure, the other ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed; the one infallible, the other vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible; the one founded by my ſelfe from the beginning, and vpon a Rocke; the other newly reared by mans imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, cheriſhed for pollicy, hauing no other ground then flitting and foundring ſand, the one intituled by preſcription, the other ſetled in poſſeſſion, the one e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by diuine prouidence, the other ſeazed by intruſion, (and to be briefe) the one mine, the other <hi>Belzebubs,</hi> the one diuine, the other Deuiliſh. Where are my indifferent mates, that can beare two faces in one hood, carry fire in one hand, and water in the other, that can breathe both hotte and cold, that can hold with the Hare and runne with the Hound: Weather-cocks vvhich turne with the winde: Camelions transforming their hew, according to the preſent object which they ſee. Let them vnfould the whole ſardle of their fancies, and bring me forth the golden meane, which they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16437:17"/> ſo much commend.</p>
            <p>Combine me fire and vvater in one bundle; make me vnderſtand (oh ye Neuters) how theſe two faiths can be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iled together, or conſtitute one faithful company, being ſo oppoſite, that of neceſſity the one muſt be plaine blaſphemy, or the other Idolatry: For as much as my dreadful Euchariſt is irreſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gably beleeued by the one, to be my true body; not in figure, but in verity; not in conceipt, but in <hi>re;</hi> not in ſhadow, but in ſubſtance; not in faith only, but by my perſonal preſence, and conſequently is adored with due veneration, whereas by Hugonots and other Heretikes it is inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly reuiled, vpbraided as an Idol, torne, ſpit at, and troden vnder foote (beaſtly Monſters as they are.) Of other maine differences, conſider vvith your ſelues the particularities; in number of Sacraments, in vſe of Images, in inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Saints, in forgiueneſſe of Sinnes, in heauenly Glory, in Infernal paines, in Iuſtification of the liuing, in praying for the Dead, in Faith, Hope, and Charity,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16437:18"/> in Faſtings and Praiers, in Sinne and Merit, in Predeſtination and Free-wil, in Scriptures, in Traditions, and almoſt in the whole ſumme of Faith. Shal <hi>Arius, Neſtorius,</hi> and <hi>Eutiches</hi> with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther old Heretikes be juſtly credited, by vniuerſal conſent of al ages, and by your owne verdicts to roare in the bottome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe pit for one or two points (for further they went not) and ſtagger ye vvhat to thinke of them, who haue toſſed ouer euery ſtone, reuerſed the whole frame of faith, and turned al vpſide-downe? Or is not rather their departure, and diuiſion from my Church, a ſufficient vvarrant of their judgement, though but in one point only, they varied from the faith.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">19. How ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and Churches of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>Caluiniſme then being doctrine ſo dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical; what are the fruits thereof? what are al thinges which depend vpon it, or are annexed thereunto? Haue this for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, vvhatſoeuer concurreth with my ſaith, concurreth with me; and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hath affinity with hereſie, conſpireth with Sathan, who is the father of lying, and foſterer of falſhood. You miſtake
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16437:18"/> much, if you take their Scriptures to be my word: Fie, none of mine, they are the word of the Deuil, falſe adulterated, poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, peruerted, ful of corruptions, which belie me in euery leafe, and make my ſpirit to ſpeake thinges, which I neuer thought, oppugning my faith and church, for whoſe maintenance and comfort they were inſpired, I diſclaime from them as from a counterfaite copy, and reuounce them as no deede of mine.</p>
            <p>You erre if you thinke their praiers to be praiers, whatſoeuer they ſay,<note place="margin">Hierom. in c. 4. Oſee.</note> whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they ſing, it is in my eares the howling of Wolues, the bellowing of Bulles, the ſcreetching of Owles, the mutual anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of night Rauens in the deſerts. Oh how illuſion bewitcheth you: if yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deeme Miniſters to ſucceede in the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of my chaire, and participate in my keies, they are of hereſie hereſies, penſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, officers of Antichriſt, his Heralds, his Prolocutors, his Scribes, his Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, his fore-runners, his Apoſtles, and the Angels of his Kingdome. Leſſe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to the body is to ſucke Adders egges,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16437:19"/> then to the ſoule miniſtration of their prophane bread; and better it were to ſwil the dregges of a fatal boule, then to ſippe the cup of their communion. Their rites and ceremonies, though few and fantaſtical, yet not a little noiſome and infectious. They are not holy, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane; not religious, but ſacriligious; yea, euen thoſe which they retaine of the auncient cuſtome, as Faſtes and Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies, which ſithence they haue tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to vnder-propping of their ſuperfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial and ruinous edifice, and to diſguiſing of their falſe ware and fradulent traſh, doe pleaſe me euen as much as a man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth to be wounded with his owne blade, and diſpighted with his owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions. Yea their Churches and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples (be not carried away with the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed phraſe) are no more holy, no more my houſe, no more the place of my Sanctification.</p>
            <p>They were, they were mine; but then mine, when none of theirs; for becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming theirs, they ceaſed to be mine. Why cal you that mine which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16437:19"/> poſſeſſed, and polluted by my e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimies? My aduerſary, yea your aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, and the aduerſary of al mankinde, boaſteth in the ſeate which was holy, and hath placed his chaire of peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, where the ſacred Altar my earthly Throneſtood. In ſteade of Quyres of Angels,<note place="margin">Chryſ.</note> which carſt frequented about it, deſcending and aſcending (though mortal eies were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of the ſight) as the dignity of my preſence required, legions of infernal ſpirits there now daunce, (though for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerting your mindes, they bewray not themſelues) triumphing not only as in their moſt proper reſidence and Pallace, but more, as in a ſubdued fort, victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly obtained againſt me. Woe to the betraiers, that of faint courage, firſt gaue ouer my hold, and rendred my ſigniory; and woe to al thoſe which ſhal thither now goe, to yeeled their homage and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leageance. The honour which there is exhibited, keepeth courſe of ſpeech by pretence of my name, but in verity touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not me, but is appropriate to <hi>Lucifer,</hi> who alwaies affecting to paragonize the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16437:20"/> higheſt, his hatred is ſo ſtrong; his enuy ſo cankred, his inſolency ſo haughty, that he reckoneth as nothing al other ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, which Heathens and Pagans vnto him exhibite, except he may draw to himſelfe, whatſoeuer is wont to be mine, and magnifie himſelfe with the brauery of my plume.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 12. &amp; 31. 1. Reg. 10.</note>Bethel vvas my houſe, where <hi>Iacob</hi> and the Patriarkes both adored and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed, but after King <hi>Hieroboam</hi> had cut off Iſrael from Hieruſalem,<note place="margin">3. Reg. 12. &amp; 13.</note> and had there erected a Religion, Prieſts, and Sacrifices, of his owne inuention? vvas Bethel any more my houſe?<note place="margin">Deutr. 11. &amp; 17.</note> Garazim I ordained for a hil of benediction; but when the Samaritans vſurped it for a place of their adoration,<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.</note> was it any longer a hil of benediction?<note place="margin">Geneſ. 12.</note> Sichem where I appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>Abraham,</hi> was a place ſanctified and adorned by him, in memory thereof with an Altar, but when the Schiſmatical people had made it the<note n="*" place="margin">3. Reg. 12 Iohn. 4. Where Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by S. Hierom to be al one with Sichem.</note> Metrapolitane See of their ſeparation, was Sichem from thence-forth ſacred? Or are the Turkiſh meſquits houſes of diuine praier, becauſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16437:20"/> they were in times paſt Chriſtian Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches? No more then <hi>Iudas</hi> was the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the holy Ghoſt, after the tempter had inuaded his hart, when the place is ſo prophane, becauſe of the ſeruice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in exerciſed, what can the ſeruice it ſelfe be but meere abhomination?</p>
            <p>Oh thinke not it can be to my worſhip which is ſo wicked. Remember,<note place="margin">20. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants publike praier, how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful &amp; deteſtable</note> that Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar is raiſed vp againſt Altar, Prieſts ſet vp againſt Prieſts, Sacraments againſt Sacraments, Seruice againſt Seruice, Faith againſt Faith, betweene vvhich there is not, (neither poſſible can be) any vnity concord or conformity; Or to ſpeake more properly, and not by the common peoples tearmes, vvho i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnorantly confound the names of thinges cal to minde, that againſt my venerable Altar, there is erected a plaine commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion Table, in defiance of the pretious and veritable Hoſt (my owne quickning and ſanctifying Body) is exalted, the Idol of their contemptible Supper, a baſe and vnprofitable peece of bread, in liew of my anointed Prieſtes, are
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16437:21"/> obtruded the Miniſters of darkeneſſe, for a reuerent, worthy, ſound, and vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted faith, is crept in baſtard, counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faite, vncertaine, and fained miſcreance.</p>
            <p>If Maſſe and Mattins, were fully and wholy vſed in their aſſemblies, and that publike praier had nothing of their owne corruption, yet were it abhominable in my ſight, proceeding from their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, who haue runne away from my Church, and ſtolen away with them her ornaments; and to couer the ragges where with they are rigde; jet vp and downe, cladde in her robes. Can the veile of a Virgin, make a ſtrumpet honeſt, or ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len attire beautifie hereſie? Is this any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then with Iewes to bow the knee, and ſpit in my face, to crowne vvith thornes, and then ſalute as King.</p>
            <p>If the ſeruice (I ſay) were perfectly Catholike, yet wil I giue no licence and leaue to Sacrifice in Aegypt, but wil be ſerued among a chaſt generation, and rather in the deſert, then among the Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians. How then ſhal I brooke a forme of praier, a ſhadow of diuine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16437:21"/> wholy tending to maintenance of hereſie, not only abrogating, diſanulling, ſuppreſſing, my auncient and approued rites, but directly ſubſtituted in defiance of me and my miſteries, and of the faith Catholike, which is put into Engliſh, to inſinuate that my Church erreth in not vſing the vulgar; blotteth out inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Saints, as open Idolatry; and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for the dead, as plaine ſuperſtition; cancelleth Conſecration, as vanity and falſhood; abhorreth Eleuation, as dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable impiety; praieth expreſly for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of their Sect, and in impreca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, joyneth <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſour (the Rocke of ſaith) with the Mahumetan Potentate, and his confederates.</p>
            <p>See here the ſeruice, which they who mocke me, cal mine, and they who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude themſelues, name the old ſeruice tranſlated: where are the memories and r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>ntations of my Saints? (leſſons of inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>on to the ignorant, and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ety to the ſimple) are they not diſpitefully broken and brent as Idols? where is my ſtandert, the eternal monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:16437:22"/> of my triumph, at the ſight where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the ſuries quake, and whoſe ſight is to euery good Chriſtian as a ſentence, heard or read out of my paſſion? where are my Tapers, which warne people, to ſee that their life be light, and their ſoules free from darkeneſſe? where are the Veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Veſſels of ſanctification, doth not the face of al thinges in their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, import a perfect and abſolute alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in faith: doe not the very walles &amp; pillers cry out, that Catholikes ſhould not come there? Ah ye poore Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical ſoules, how long vvil ye erre and runne forward without remorſe, if reaſon ſtay you not, regard the examples of conſtancy, which ſtand before your eies; and how faithful beleeuers behaue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">21. Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly build vpon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious examples.</note>You can ſay that Prieſts did in many Pariſhes follow the new courſe, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them yet liuing, continue in the ſame. And why rather leane ye not vnto the example of the Biſhops, vvhom no leſſe learning and ſanctity then their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours function, more commend vnto
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16437:22"/> you; vvho vniuerſaly died in long and lingring impriſonment, no one yeelding to vnconſcionable conformity, but rather chooſing to looſe both liuings and liberty and to ſee their aduerſaries poſſeſſe their chaires. Oh but great Preſidents moue you, and many wiſe fellowes haue aſſaied this Ice before you. Ye pry vpon the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupteſt ſoules, as Kites when they ſeeke a carkaſſe; and like the Rauen, vvhich <hi>Noe</hi> let flie, ye rather wil ſtay your ſelues vpon a carrion, then returne to the Arke. Why rather returne ye not vvith the Doue, although ye ſhould haue found greene boughes, whereon to recline? you propoſe to your weary and tired ſpirit, to your fainting harts, the examples of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine which ſeeme to you wiſe, but are in very deede ſooles; ſeeme learned, are ignorant; ſeeme religious, are meere worldlings.</p>
            <p>Aſwel you might build, that theft, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortion, murder, or adultery, vvere no wickedneſſe, becauſe they ſometimes fal into theſe ſinnes, whom a falſe ſhew of wiſdome or vertue had before co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:16437:23"/> Euery man that ſinneth, doth not ſtraight thinke it lawful, wil you direct your life by his rule, who perhaps condemneth his owne, yet if any wil ſtifly defend their Schiſme, to cleare themſelues from ſinne, is this ſufficient ſecurity, to follow ſuch mens fantaſies? where haue theſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors the k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of knowledge; vvhence fetcht theſe Doctors them profound lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning? where waded they, through the depthes of diuinity? No man in his waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty cauſe truſteth the warrant of a puny ſtudent, contrary to the opinion of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailors, no man crediteth his life to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aw practiſioner, againſt the aduiſe of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tenſed Phiſition. And wil ye hazard your ſoules vpon a preſumptuous ſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s conj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cture, neglecting what they teach, whoſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly labour is to guide to heauen; whoſe life and ſtudy is the daily meditation of my law.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">22. Examples fit to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>garded by Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</note>Why <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ather ſix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ye not before your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies, ſo many both of the ſpiritualty and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity, who haue in your owne memory, but yeſterday, yea daily, ſuſtained blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ignominious death, rather then
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16437:23"/> runne your race and incurre damnation? Walke to the priſons, ſee if they be not ful of my Confeſſors? there haue you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples juſtly to be imbraced, not one but many, not many but multitudes.</p>
            <p>If thinges preſent pleaſe you not, caſt your regard vpon ages paſt, conſider what the faithful in al antiquity hath beene wont to doe in like caſe, as yours is now. Weigh what <hi>Tobias</hi> would haue done in theſe times,<note place="margin">Tob. 1.</note> who when al Iſrael fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented the Calues of <hi>Hieroboam,</hi> though he were of their Tribes, yet would neuer beare them company, but contrary to the Kinges ordinance, and the peoples pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, went yearely to adore at Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, what thoſe religious hartes would haue performed, who being Iſraelites for ſooke their natiue Country, becauſe of the Schiſme,<note place="margin">1. Paral. 15.</note> and went to dwel in Iuda vnder a right beleeuing Prince.</p>
            <p>What conſtancy the ſeauen Brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren would haue ſhewed,<note place="margin">Mac. 7.</note> who were ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed by vnſpeakeable torments, for refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to eate ſwines fleſh, at King <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus</hi> commandement, becauſe it was
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:16437:24"/> an act abhorring from the profeſſion of their law.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Mach. 6.</note>How would <hi>Eleazarus</hi> haue behaued himſelfe, who gladly ſuffered death, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to giue ſcandal by ſeeming conformable to the ſame wicked decrees, refuſing moſt conſtantly ſo to diſſemble, as publikely to eate meates, not forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den indeede by <hi>Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſes,</hi> yet proffered vnto him, and pretended to the beholders as ſwines fleſh, thereby outwardly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcending to the Infidels proceedings.</p>
            <p>How reſolute would <hi>Machabeus</hi> haue beene, how couragious his Sonnes? What a firery and zealous anſwere gaue the Father to the Kinges Commiſſioners, exacting his obedience to the late edicts, concerning alteration in religion. <hi>If al men obey the Kinges commandements, yet I and my Sonnes wil neuer doe it.</hi> If to theſe Preſidents ye pleade that <hi>Moyſes</hi> was greater then I, my ſeruant then my ſelfe, that more perfection and zeale was to be required of Iewes, then of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that my old Teſtament, was more holy and more preciſely to be ſtood vpon
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16437:24"/> then my new, bethinke your ſelues of my Apoſtles and Diſciples, whoſe heires and imitatours as ye pretend to be in faith, ſo ye ought to be in profeſſion.</p>
            <p>Would <hi>Peter</hi> thinke you haue broo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Luther,</hi> founder and grand-father of ſo many falſhoods, who for one article of misbeleefe, bidde <hi>Simon Magus</hi> auaunt as ful of bitter gal, and the child of perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Would <hi>Paul</hi> haue ſpared Miniſters the ſeducers of many ſoules, who ſtoutly called <hi>Elymas</hi> the Deuils Sonne,<note place="margin">Act. 13.</note> and eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of righteouſneſſe, for diſwading one man from the faith, &amp; by his word ſtroke him with blindneſſe? Would my diuine Euangeliſt <hi>S. Iohn</hi> haue endured <hi>Iohn Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin</hi> that Arch-heretike, the corrupter of whole Prouinces, who at the ſight of pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Cerinthus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iren. lib. 3. cap. 3. Euſeb. hiſt Eccl. lib. 3. cap. 22.</note> ſubuerter not of the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands perſon, in compariſon of the other, cried out to the people, that they ſhould flie from his company, leaſt the place where they were, together ſhould for <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthus</hi> ſake fal vpon their head. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps theſe pillers of my church, would to ſaue their goods or liues, haue reuerently
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:16437:25"/> heard the common praiers of <hi>Simon, Elymas,</hi> and <hi>Corinthus,</hi> honoured their abhominations, and receiued communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on bread at their handes. What appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended ye of al my auncient Martirs? thouſands of whom each day through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the yeare, hath regiſtred in the booke of life, and crowned with an immortal Garland, becauſe they would not partake with Idolaters, in any act of their vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">23. Participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in workes of Hereſie worſe then in actes of Idolatry.</note>If now you be ſo ſimple, as to thinke that Hereſie is not worſe then Idolatry; that to forſake me, is not worſe then ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to haue followed me; to deny me, then not to confeſſe me; to abjure me, then not to know me; to blaſpheme, then not to honour me; that Infidels for their ignorance, ſhal be beaten vvith many ſtripes, and Hereſie for her peruerſneſſe; malice and apoſtacy ſhal be beaten, with few; that to caſt two or three graines of Francumcenſe vpon a Heathen Altar; or to lay a bunch of Grapes before <hi>Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Syndas Nicepho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus.</note> to crowne <hi>Ceres</hi> with cares of corne; to moue a little the bonnet before <hi>Iupiter</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:16437:25"/> be greater ſacrilege, then the courteſie of cappe and knee, and reuerential pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, at their thriſe Idolatrous commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; or then the ſeruice to maintenance thereof erected; euery jot of whoſe ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual cuſtomes, and publike praiers vvas inuented, commanded, practiſed, and is ſtil continued, only in deteſtation, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance, extirpation, and denial of my faith Catholike.</p>
            <p>Then, oh then how are ye deceiued?<note place="margin">24. Hereſie worſe then Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity and Idolatry.</note> ſeing euery falſhood, the more it hath of truth, is the more apt to beguile; the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re apt to beguile, the more pernitious to the diſtruction of ſoules, and more abhominable. Falſe Prophets which cry <hi>the Lord, the Lord,</hi> when I the Lord haue not ſpoken vnto them, are worſe ten-fold then the Prophets of <hi>Baal,</hi> ſooner ſhal the Publican be juſtified, then the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical Pharaſie, viler and more hateful before me and men is the Adultreſſe, which by Matronlike demeanure would ſeeme a Saint, then the open Strumpet which carrieth lightneſſe on her backe, and vanity in her face. A plaine fable is
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:16437:26"/> laughed at, but not hated, becauſe it is not made to deceiue, neither is apt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt if the authour would, but a lie for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and obtruded for truth is intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; Yet if ſo be that wilfulneſſe hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed reaſon, that whereas you are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to die, rather then yeeld to Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try (for ſo now and then you would make your ſelues beleeue) yet you would yeeld to hereſie, rather then ſuſtaine any da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage.</p>
            <p>Reflect then once at my requeſt, vpon my good Chriſtians, whom (Idolatry be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ouer-come) I exerciſed by Arianiſme; ſome-what alwaies, being neceſſary to try my elect. Reſtect (I ſay) your vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding vpon their excellent zeale: (except perhaps ye refuſe with ſoare eies, to behold the Sunne, for feare of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter annoy) marke wel how they forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied their faith againſt the Arrian Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Socrat. l. 2. c. 12.22.23.24. Theod. l. 4. cap. 14. Niceph. l. 9. cap. 24.</note>Regard how in Greece, they vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the Proclamations of <hi>Valens</hi> the Emperor, chooſing rather to be ſcorched, brent, ſlaine, at their aſſemblies without
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:16437:26"/> the Church walles, then they would be preſent at publike praier of their here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Superintendent, though their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice which he ſaid were nothing altered from their owne;<note place="margin">Victor Vtic. de perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalorum.</note> ſet before your eies the horrible calamities, and intollerable vexations, vvhich Catholikes in Africa endured, vnder their Vandal Princes, for refuſing to partake with them in their Arrian rites, and for priuately frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Maſſe, vvhen it was forbidden.</p>
            <p>Finally, muſter before your ſelues the Martirs and Confeſſors of al ages, from the beginning of the vvorld, to this preſent time, from <hi>Abel</hi> to the laſt which you haue ſeene (or might haue ſeene) with your owne eies. Let the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry names of <hi>Martir</hi> and <hi>Confeſſor</hi> exhort you: the firſt whereof admoniſheth you,<note place="margin">Martir ſignifieth witneſſe.</note> that I require your teſtimony: refuſe not therefore to beare witneſſe of my truth; the other that I challenge your ſuite and ſeruice at my Court, your duty and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance at my feaſts, your vaſſalage and alleageance confeſſe therefore and deny me not.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:16437:27"/>
            <p>Oh ye ſtubborne bowes, which wil ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther breake then come to the juſt bent, which the true meaſure of Chriſtianity requireth? Oh peruerſe generation, how much ye want of the perfection of aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient beleeuers? Nay, how much want ye of the true zeale, which a number of good ſoules declare, on whom yet I haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed leſſe gifts, either of nature or of worldly proſperity? In caſe you ſay to your ſelues, that you ſee not the actions of auncient times, yet the example and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of theſe, doth euery day in euery place hitte you on the eies, and might wound your hartes, if they were fleſh, and not of flint: nay, if they were not too fleſhy, and voide of al ſpirit. How juſt cauſe haue I then to exclaime againſt you (oh diſloyal wreatches) how long wil ye reject my authority, and kicke againſt my Commandements?<note place="margin">25. By what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God going to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiks prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden.</note> who am I that charge you? am not I the Omnipotent? who am I that cal you? am I not your Creatour? You put your hand in your boſome, and draw forth an empty excuſe from your hollow hartes, you can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:16437:27"/> no law of mine, that you brake by going to heretical ſeruice, nor can finde any precept to the contrary. I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that you are deeplier ſeene in the ſtatutes of men, then in mine ordinances, in the common law, then in the Canons, more minde the managing of ſecular af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, then of your ſoules, and better know how many yeares purchaſe a peece of land is worth, or how much a loade of corne commeth to at ſuch a rate, then what p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e heauen is to be valued at, or what ſumme of felicity merits added to merits, wil at length a mount vnto, which is that great and maine commandement, not the principal point only, but the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgement of the whole law?</p>
            <p>Is it not, that man loue me with al his hart, vvith al his ſtrength, with al his ſoule? you anſwere, this ſerueth your turne, and that you loue me aſmuch as I require: But deſcend to the particulars, and you ſhal be taken with the lie.</p>
            <p>Did I no where wil, that beſides be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing in hart, you ſhould alſo profeſſe your beleefe before men. Or vvil you
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:16437:28"/> violently make me to meane before Iews and Heathen, but not before Heretikes; in time of religion flouriſhing, but not in time of perſecution, to the obtaining of credit or commodity, but not to detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Did I not adde, that he which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth me before men, ſhal be denied of me, in the preſence of Angels. He which ſhal be aſhamed of my religion, I wil put him to open confuſion, and which ſhal ſaue his life temporally, by yeelding to the perſecutour, ſhal looſe it eternally being condemned at a more dreadful tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal, when vniuerſal Sizes are held o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer al the world.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iſay 42.</note>Haue I not ſaid, that I am a jealous God, and wil not giue my honour to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?<note place="margin">Deuter. 7.</note> Did I not ſeuerely forbidde my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to encermedle in Heatheniſſe rites? did I not for peril thereof interdict them al ſociety,<note place="margin">Exod. 23.</note> and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation with Infidels? did I not denounce by my Apoſtles pen, that as in hart men are to beleeue, that they may be juſtified,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> ſo with mouth they are to confeſſe their ſaith, that they may be ſaued? If by mouth, how much more
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:16437:28"/> by deedes, and the whole courſe of their life? Or wil I (thinke you) contrary my owne decrees, approue him which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth me in wordes, and denieth me in profeſſion?</p>
            <p>And what if I had not in ſuch expreſſe wiſe preſcribed your duty?<note place="margin">26. Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the law of nature, by going to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants Churches.</note> doth not the light of reaſon, the law of nature, the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a Chriſtian man, ſuggeſt, teach, command, that ye cleaue firmely to your faith, and that for no cauſe poſſible to be imagined, ye commit any thing, in word ordeed, or omit any thing by negligence or ſlouth, which may import a departure from your religion, or be ſo interpreted and accepted; or that may ſeeme in any one point a conformity; to a ſtrange and falſe faith, a yeelding or agreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious proceedings? If he which breaketh one commandement be guilty of al, as a violater of charity; ſhal not he likewiſe, vvhich faileth or falleth in one point of faith, be fully guilty of Infidelity? To beare truly the title of a faithful ſoule, it is not enough to beleeue a-right in one or two articles, but my whole law, that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:16437:29"/> is, the entire word <hi>of faith,</hi> muſt ſtedfaſtly be imbraced. If then I ſhal ſay; <hi>goe ye curſed,</hi> for not doing good, for omitting only hoſpitality, and workes of mercy, ſhal wickedneſſe goe ſcot-free, ſhal par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking with Heretikes in their abh mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, paſſe as innocent? Shal depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from my Church, my Faith, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, deſerue to heare: <hi>Come ye bleſſed?</hi> Is there nothing for me to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, but whether you be murtherers, theeues, or adulterers? doe I much reſpect that you ſhould not offend your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and contemne my owne injuries.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">27. Hereſie &amp; pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> purpoſely permitted of God for trial of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s harts.</note>I foretold, while I conuerſed on earth, that hereſies of neceſſity muſt be for the trial, and manifeſtation of mens hartes, that it might be apparant, who would of a proude and contemptuous ſpirit em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace hereſie, who would of faint hart and puſi lanimity obey it, who contrary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe vvould meekely trace his reuerent Fathers ſteps, and preferre the authority of the vniuerſal Church, before his owne imaginations, and not to be ſhaken as a reede, with any tempeſtes of bluſtering
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:16437:29"/> perſecution.<note place="margin">Luke 12.</note> I fore-warned that I came not to ſend peace but ſeperation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Parents and Children, Subject and Prince, Maſter and Seruant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Wife and Husband, Bretheren, Kinsfolke, and Friendes, that perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhould be raiſed on al ſides, and that he which loueth parents or children, or what elſe more then me, and wil not take vp his Croſſe and follow me,<note place="margin">Math. 10.</note> is not my Diſciple, nor worthy to haue part in my Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Are you Chriſtians,<note place="margin">25. Diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling in religion is abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable.</note> and thinke your ſelues excuſed from the precept, which I gaue to the Synagogue, that if any man would draw you to a ſtraunge faith, he ſhould not be obeyed, for that by ſuch I make proofe of my ſeruants, I diſcouer the ſecrets of the hart; and ſift the branne from the fine flowre, try the wheate from chaffe.</p>
            <p>Are you Chriſtians, and know not that to follow a falſe faith, is to ſerue a falſe God, and to beginne new and ſtraunge doctrine of faith, is to erect a new and ſtraunge Idol. If you doubt thereof, I
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:16437:30"/> aſſure you it is ſo. And now is your time of trial: now are you called vpon, ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, yea commanded to follow new do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, to ſerue <hi>Caluins</hi> Idol, now are you caſt into the furnace, now ſhal you proue your ſelues, either gold or droſſe, and the calamities of this preſent time, I haue purpoſely ſent that the ſecrets of al hartes ſhal be reuealed.</p>
            <p>Reuealed you are to your owne ſhame and to my griefe. What ſhal I doe to your ſtony hartes, to whom my ſerious commandement, of profeſſing ſincerely your ſaith by your conuerſation, is but as a puffe of winde againſt a mountaine? Shal I charge your conſciences vvith <hi>Moyſes</hi> ceremonies, and cauſe you as I did the Iewes, to beare the remembrance of this commandement vpon your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, ſeing it is ſo ſhine from your hartes. Shal I forbidde you to vveare linſey-woolſey in your raiment, to joyne in the plough the Aſſe with the Oxe, and to ſow with two kinde of ſeedes. Though theſe obſeruances were appendant to the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:16437:30"/> old law, doubt ye not but the ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, taketh place in the new. He which walketh ſimply and plainely,<note place="margin">Pro. 10.</note> walkes confidently; Diſſimulation and double-dealing, I in euery thing hate; but in factes of religion, I vtterly ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre.</p>
            <p>Admit that neither reaſon nor rule of conſcience ſuggeſted vnto you,<note place="margin">29. Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> authority of the Church.</note> nor that I expreſly exacted of you ſuch firme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of faith, yet ought not the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of my Church, to weigh ſo light in your conceipts, as neither to hearken vnto my Prieſts, who to reduce you from Heretical conuenticles, ſet nought by their liues, and haue by their bloud confirmed the thing to be vnlawful, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to accept pardon of life, vpon ſo damnable a condition; nor to my Vicat in earth, vvho ſollicitous for ſoules, ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth neither care nor coſt for your ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, nor to the declaration of my General Councel at Trent, vvhich re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued (when this caſe came firſt in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion) that not without grieuous ſacrilege,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:16437:31"/> you could yeeld your preſence, at the Heretikes Churches, or Eccleſiaſtical aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies; or by any other manner of ſigne, giue external conſent to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable rites. A thing indeede, which by men of vnderſtanding could neuer haue beene doubted off, if worldly feare had not blinded peoples harts, and made them hard to beleeue, that which plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not their humour. What can they therefore accompt themſelues, who wil not hearken to my Spouſes voice, nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey her admonition; but to be vvorſe then Heathens and Infidels.<note place="margin">Math. 17. 2. Reg.</note> Let them know, that not to obey her, is as ſac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious as Idolatry, and al that contemne her are accurſed.<note place="margin">Tob. 13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">30. Heretikes how pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly to be ſhunned.</note>Beſides that principal precept, of lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing your God aboue al; and that other abſolute ſtatute of conſtant profeſſion of my faith Catholike, which ſuffereth no exception. If you wil but a little looke about you, ye ſhal finde that I haue yet left you another commandement, as a continual helpe againſt mans frailty, a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne preſeruation againſt al infection
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:16437:31"/> of peſtilent doctrine. It is more auaile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able againſt the ſpiritual enimy, then any armour of proofe, or a ten-fold ſhield: and might in theſe darkeſome daies be a torch vnto your ſteps. Wil you beare to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are it? wil you indeauour to follow it, that my preſent admonition, may not turne to your greater damnation? you wil, if you may heare it from my owne mouth, it ſhal be joyfully receiued, as comming from heauen, your wordes are reaſonable.</p>
            <p>Wel then, whoſe ſpirit but mine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired, and eſtabliſhed as a perpetual ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, to the worldes end, that He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes ſhould be vtterly auoided, as <hi>men</hi> ſubuerted and already damned by their owne judgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t;<note place="margin">Tit. 3. Rom. 16.</note> as <hi>ſowers</hi> of ſchiſme and authors of diuiſion, by teaching con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary faith, to that which was firſt recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued;<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2. 2. Tim. 3.</note> as <hi>whoſe</hi> ſpeech creepeth like a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker; as <hi>louers</hi> of pleaſures, rather then of God, making a ſhew of piety, but deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in effect the vertue thereof;<note place="margin">Math. 7. 2. Pet. 2.</note> as <hi>Wolues</hi> in ſheepes attire; as <hi>authours</hi> of blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Sects, bold, ſelfe conceipted, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:16437:32"/> after the fleſh;<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3. 1. Ioh. 2.</note> as <hi>thoſe</hi> who follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their owne fancies and deſires, <hi>haue</hi> iſſued out from among the faithful, and <hi>fallen</hi> from the truth,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.</note> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iudae 4.</note> 
               <hi>turning</hi> the grace of God to vncleaneneſſe, and are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore already appointed to judgement; as <hi>falſe</hi> Apoſtles,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.</note> deceitful labourers, Miniſters of Sathan, whoſe end ſhal be according to their workes, and (to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude al iniquity, imaginable vnder one title) as <hi>Antichriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ioh. 2.</note> I wil not therefore, that ye eate or drinke, or haue familiarity with them,<note place="margin">Ioh. ep. 2.</note> I wil not that ye friendly <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute</hi> them, for in ſo doing you partake in their wicked workes, and bolſter them in their proccedinges, and by juſt conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent muſt be partners of their damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>How long ſhal the light of reaſon and conſcience ſleepe? how often muſt ye be admoniſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, that right beleeuers muſt not participate with Infidels; that I can haue no ſociety with <hi>Belial:</hi> nor my cup vvith the cup of Deuils. If light and darkeneſſe can loue? If I joyne in any reſpect with <hi>Lucifer,</hi> if euer any mercy,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:16437:32"/> loue, or amity, any league or conſent, be betweene him and me, then let Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes adhere to Heretikes. If no ſuch thing can poſſibly be, but that eternal enmity bee ſworne betweene vs, why then ſhould children of Hieruſalem, come to the ſolemnities of Babylon? they which looke to be heires of heauen, make pact with hel? expecters of life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting, marchandiſe for their tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral with accurſed death? He that run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth with the theefe, fornicateth with the adulterer, murthereth with the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, is in no caſe to be excuſed, no not although they doe it for feare, more then for affection to the ſinne.</p>
            <p>Shal they then vvhich profeſſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, with Heretikes bee found cleare? Of like I had no reaſon to forbidde you their company,<note place="margin">31. Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes are infected with he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie and not with pure Schiſme only.</note> for you are proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and diſcreet, firmely grounded in the Catholike faith, ſtronge Rockes, vvhome no vvaues nor tempeſtes can moue, vveake vvreatches, and ſo much the vveaker, by how much you preſume more of your ſelues, and rely
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:16437:33"/> more vpon your owne indeauours, then vpon my grace: how feeble ye are, your actions giue better teſtimony, then your imaginations.</p>
            <p>Are ye they, which can liue in the fire, and not be ſcorched in the flame, and not be ſmothered; wade vp to the lippe in the ſurges of the Sea, and not be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed; handle pitch and not be defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, eate and drinke, conuerſe, contract, (not only bargaines, but marriages) di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſport, diſcourſe, play, pray, liue and die vvith Heretikes; and yet ſound at my terrible examen, neither attached with their infection, nor touched with conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion? I fore-warned my auncient and firſt people, that if they vſed the conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of Infidels, among whom they dwelt,<note place="margin">Ioſ. 23.</note> they ſhould finde them ſtumbling blockes of ſcandal, by giuing occaſion of ruine, and prickes to their eies, in put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out the inward light of faith, what by example, what by cuſtome and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion. Experience proueth this true in them, and the euent argueth it more true in yourſelues.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:16437:33"/>
            <p>Are not moſt of you infected, ſome with one hereſie, ſome with another? I haue to charge you withal, beſides go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Church, how ſoeuer you thinke your ſelues, to be ſome-what vertuous, and Godly; Rarer then a white Crow is he to be found among you, who either cancelleth not faſting-daies by his owne authority, or diſpenſeth not with meates prohibited, as often as he liſt, or doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not of ſome article of faith, if not of al? One improueth Confeſſion, another Purgatory, this man inuocation of Saints or vſe of Images, that man praiers for the Dead, or the office in Latin. There are that ſuppoſe Antichriſt ſhal not be one ſingular perſon, but includeth a company or a ſucceſſion. Many doubt nothing of this, yet acknowledge no vnion of the Church, vnder one head viſible; or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract from the authority of Councels, and decrees Eccleſiaſtical: Moſt of you feare leaſt the gates of hel haue preuailed againſt my Rocke; leaſt the ſpirit which I gaue her, haue not fulfilled my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, neither taught her al truth, but
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:16437:34"/> that ſhee may diuerſly erre.</p>
            <p>The ſtench of the damnable memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the fume of their brimſtone, aſcendeth from the bottomleſſe lake, who of Schiſmatikes haue at laſt become flat Heretikes, yea Perſecutours, yea and of an il beginning, made a vvorſe ending?<note place="margin">3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. By what meanes Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes grow to be He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes.</note> vvhence al this? not becauſe the longer ye liue, the skilfuller ye waxe in Diuinity, the carefuller of your ſoules, more deſirous of heauen, or are oftner viſited with inſpirations celeſtial, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye vvaxe weary of expecting my pleaſure, in that I come not at your ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, but let my ſecret and eternal prouidence haue the determinate courſe, ye thinke I haue either forgotten my Church, or caſt her off; ſuppoſing quite contrary to Chriſtian doctrine, that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity is an abſolute ſigne of my indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of a reprobate religion. Wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more and more in loue vvith the world, ye haue leſſe ſence and feeling of remorſe? by neuer talking with Prieſts, nor conferring of matters touching the ſpirit; by being loden with ſecret ſinnes,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:16437:34"/> which either you wil not acknowledge, or minde not to forſake, or cannot be indured to reforme by reſtitution and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction; it commeth to paſſe, partly through the nature of ſuch negligence, partly through my juſt permiſſion, for your vngratitude toward me, that you beginne to loath the religion, vvhich checketh your humour, and aſſureth not heauen to ſinne and iniquity.</p>
            <p>Amidſt theſe your ſenſual, carnal, and worldly affections, hereſie buſzeth ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out your eares, plauſibly inuiting you to her cuppe of pleaſure. Thus lying open to the enimy, and deſtitute of my grace and protection, you are made a pray to the roring Lyon; vvhile with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſing among Heretikes, ye become like them in life. Becomming like them in conditions, you quickly delight in their ſutable doctrine. Poyſon, poyſon, lurketh in their company, as in domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Adders, and in the familiarity as in Cocatrice eies. What though at the firſt ye be not Conquered? He which loueth peril, ſhal periſh therein:
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:16437:35"/> vvhat though their arguments be but weake and fooliſh? Drops of raine in continuance pearce the hardeſt ſtone, a ſmal worme in time decaieth the roote of the faireſt Vine, and contemptible Yui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> being let alone, ouer-creep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th and ouer maſtereth in time the tal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt tree. Flee therefore ſociety of Heretikes (aſmuch as you may) euen in temporal buſineſſe, becauſe of your peril, and becauſe my counſaile is ſo to doe. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee it abſolute in fact of religion, not for peril only, but for ſinne, not becauſe of my aduiſe only, but for my commandement ſake. Flee Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon, flee Chore, flee Sodome, flee from the aduerſary campe in time, as ye wil at the day of my victory, at the day of your death, at the great day of judgement, not be taken for enimies.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">33. The obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy of Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes and ingratitude towardes God.</note>Perceiue ye not, for al that I can ſay or doe, the horror of your offence, (oh ye my traitours and rebels) how long ſhal I cry out to a people, which haue ſtopped their eares, and alleage reaſon to them, which ſay they wil not vnderſtand? how long ſhal I preach repentance to them,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:16437:35"/> which repel knowledge, and catch hold vpon euery ſimple ſhift, as vpon a ſtaffe to ſuſtaine their halting and trembling conſciences. The eare diſcerneth wordes, and the eies coulours, the mouth taſtes: This rude wilful people hath reaſon, and yet diſcerueth not iniquity. They repel al outward admonitions, for fea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e they ſhould be conuicted; ſecret inſpiration of contrition, they reject as melancholly; remorſe of conſcience, they hate as a hart ſore.</p>
            <p>Shal I for this hold my peace, and leaue to lay open their faultes? If it be little that I haue yet alleaged againſt you, heare more if it be not too little, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to condemne you, and too too much for you to finde any euaſion, yet wil I adde more, to ſee if any thing can moue you; yea though nothing w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l moue you, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wal I adde it to j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtifie your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, and my complaint, woe, woe, to you who wil not know the time of your viſitation.</p>
            <p>Behold, I haue ſtoode at the dore, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to be let into you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hartes, and you
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:16437:36"/> haue not opened vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o me, when there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye ſhal deſire to enter into my King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and reſt I wil anſwere you, that which the fooliſh Virgins heard, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h ſorrow enough: <hi>Ye come to late, the gate is ſhut, and it ſhal neuer more be opened.</hi> I haue ſought reſt in your ſoules, to make there my manſion, and I finde as at my natiuity,<note place="margin">Luke 1.</note> that <hi>there is no place in the Inne;</hi> I muſt ſeeke ſome-where elſe. I come to your boundes and territories, to caſt out your Deuils, and heale your infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties:<note place="margin">Math. 8.</note> you like ſecond <hi>Geraſens,</hi> becauſe of temporal loſſe of your Swine, requeſt me to depart your confines.</p>
            <p>I wil depart, and when in neceſſity you cal me backe, I wil not returne. I inuite my ſelfe to your dinner, as I did to <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus,</hi> to worke in your houſe ſaluation; ye con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rary to him refuſe my courteſie, and wil no ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>luation to your houſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. I wil ſeeke more worthy Hoſtes, and I wil ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke off the duſt of my feete againſt you. I cal you as <hi>Lazarus</hi> foure daies dead, (foure yeares dead, if not fourty) out of your ſtinking graues; I cry <hi>come forth,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:16437:36"/> come forth,</hi> and ye wil not ariſe. Poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly you imagine, that as I in raiſing <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus,</hi> brake the common courſe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to ſhew my glory, ſo I wil in you ſwarue from the ſtatute of your creation, and violating your free vvil, make you Catholikes by force ſo to ſaue you, wel lie ſtil in your putrifaction, whom my voice could not raiſe to ſaluation, my Angels ſhal raiſe them to judgement. I haue ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ong ſtoode and cryed: <hi>Ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich trauaile and are loden come vnto me, and I wil refreſh you.</hi> I haue openly proclaimed that vvhoſoeuer thirſteth, ſhould come vnto me, and I wil giue him drinke of the water of life. Which importunate indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours of mine, and vehement prouocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſince they nothing auaile, ſeing ye contemne my loue, and ſet not by the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of my mercy. I am forced to an our cry againſt you: <hi>O al ye which paſſe by the way, behold and ſee if there be any griefe like vnto mine?</hi> See if any man were euer ſo handled by his enimies, as I their God by my creatures. See if euer ſo great kindneſſe hath beene recompenſed
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:16437:37"/> with ſo monſtrous vngratitude: if Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s were euer ſo diſpighted by their Subjects, Lordes by their Vaſſals. See if at any time beggarly neceſſity deſpiſed ſo bountiful munificence; or apparant peril of ruine and vtter deſtruction, were ſo ſecurely neglected. See if any memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry can record ſo high a Majeſty, to haue loued ſo affectionally as baſe a bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maide, and to haue beene ſo ignomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly repulſed in his ſuite.</p>
            <p>What fettered caitiues were euer cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to ſuch glorious liberty, and would not come out of their dungeons? What languiſhing in ſuch loathſome malladies were proffered health, and loued better their noiſome calamity? Conſider and ſee how the Courtly cares, the Royal cheare, which I haue prepared for my feaſt,<note place="margin">Luke 14.</note> hath beene fruſtrate and diſgraced by vnworthy companions: one excuſeth himſelfe by cares, an other by couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, an other by caruality, one hath buſineſſe, an other is bargaining, the third hath married and cannot come. Nay ye ſhal not come? but the time ſhal
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:16437:37"/> come when like dogges, ye ſhal hunger and runne about ſearching, and ſhal not finde for your famine. Ye ſhal craue and wiſh, cry and cal for the crummes, which ſhal fal from my childrens table, and from the trenchers of my houſe-hold, but ſhal not obtaine them, ye ſhal roare after one draught of wate to allay your thirſt, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhal it be reached: yet vvhen you haue done your worſt, by not comming when ye were called; my banquet ſhal not be blemiſhed. I wil oppoſe to your ſoules of better talent, you fruſtrate my feaſt, but it ſhal not be fruſtrate, I wil fil it with better gueſtes; you diſgrace it, but I vvil grace it with more honourable roomes; ye ſhal be eternally barred from the table of the Lambe, Heretikes ſhal enter before you into my Kingdome, Heretikes ſhal be conuerted, to ſupply your place; and Infidels wil I fetch from Eaſt and Weſt India, to ſit in my glory, and ye ſhal be throwne into vtter darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. They ſhal poſſeſſe the Thrones ordained for you; they ſhal enjoy the Crowne, which hong ouer your heades,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:16437:38"/> in expectation of your de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erts. Faith ſhal be giuen to them, to them ſhal th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ace be tranſlated which ye ref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe, and they ſhal fulfil the righteouſneſſe belonging to their b leefe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">34. Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their euil example impugne the Catho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aith.</note>But oh that only ye loſt your owne Crownes, and that ye were not occaſion of perdition to thouſands more. Oh that though ye honour me not your ſelues, yet that ye would not worke me that contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely and reproch, which I may not beare at your handes. Euery where am I bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemed through your example, my reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion growing in contempt, becauſe ye ſet ſo little by it, who are thought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it. The edifice which I ſo care<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ully founded, ye like mouldring ſtones decay by your faltring and relenting, that which my Saints haue built by their bloud (or rather I by mine owne) ye ruinate by the world and fleſh, as faſt as zeale laboureth to kindle holly flame, ſo faſt doth your coldneſſe extinguiſh it. Marke how de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate my houſe is, and how many haue forſaken my Church, one through an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others example. It is your diſſimulation
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:16437:38"/> that betraieth my cauſe, without which perſecution could little preuaile. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction and confirmation to your er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, ye ſet the examples of others before your eies, as pillers of your actions, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhal make you the ground of their vngodlineſſe.</p>
            <p>The contagion runneth among you from one to an other: as Chored ſheepe and blaſted fruit, ye daily are deſtroied and deſtroy by mutual infection, you ſay you hurt not me or my cauſe, but the joy of the aduerſary, and the dole of the Catholikes conuinceth it. If you could now ſee the triumph, vvhich you adorne for the Deuil, and the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of the Angels and Saints, as you ſhal one day know it, you vvould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe no leſſe, then I now charge you vvithal, in the meane ſpace that which you ſee in the Children of light, and in the Children of darkeneſſe, how the one is grieued, the other encouraged, and how each ſide laboureth, the one to vvinne you, the other to hold you faſt, is ſufficient to informe you and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:16437:39"/> condemne you, becauſe <hi>Moyſes</hi> and <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> did once by their example not ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie me, I would neuer let them enter the land of promiſe, and ſhal you enter into my reſt, who diſhonour me before peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple euery day? He which is the ruine of one poore ſoule, were better be drowned with a milſtone, and thinke ye it a ſleight matter to deſtroy, ye knowe not your ſelues how many? The children of Iſrael repining againſt the difficulties which they found, when I ledde them through the laborious deſert, (as I now conduct my Church in England, through the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couth dreadful and paineful waies of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction and tribulation) I cauſed them euery one to die in the wilderneſſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept only <hi>Ioſua</hi> and <hi>Caleb,</hi> becauſe they two aſmuch as in them lay, encouraged forward the reſt. Shal then your mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring and rebelling againſt the croſſes, laid vpon my flocke eſcape my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? Wherein chiefly lay the ſinne of <hi>Ophin</hi> and <hi>Phines,</hi> for which I plagued both their father, their children, and al their poſterity? was it not the alienating
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:16437:39"/> and diſcouraging of people from my ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice by prejudicial behauiour? wil any King going to warre-fare endure him, which ſhal by faint wordes or cowardly examples, detract the journey and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue the Souldiers hartes from battaile? I ſuppoſe not: for one ſuch perſon hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth more then ſeauen enimies, if he vvould; ſhould he not build with one hand, and pul downe with the other? How then can ye be excuſed from being both impediments and impugners, of my religion? ſeing as in skirmiſh, ſo in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention about religion, the apprehenſion of man and his frailty is ſuch, that if one ſhrinke ten faint, and if ten yeeld a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred flie; and diuers not ſtanding to their tackling, the ouerthrow of al followeth, and ſlaughter of the reſt.</p>
            <p>Oh ye fugitiues from my pauilions and campe, ye cal me King,<note place="margin">35. Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe God.</note> but where is your ſubjection, you cal me Captaine, but where is your courage? you cal me Lord, but where is yours ſeruice? ye cal me father, but where is your fillial loue? ye cal me Sauiour, but where is your care
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:16437:40"/> of ſaluation? ye cal me Redeemer, but where is your thankefulneſſe? ye cal me Creatour, but where is your obedience and loue? ye cal me Omnipotent, yet ye feare not my power; ye cal me juſt, yet feare not my rodde; ye cal me w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe, yet thinke not that I pearce your diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; ye cal me merciful, yet accept not my pardon, which I here offer you yet againe, if ye wil preſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly repent. Ye cal me good, yet vſe it not, but abuſe my goodneſſe: ye cal me righteous, yet doe me wrong: ye cal me God, yet haue more reſpect of man. Ye ſay ye are not wicked, but what greater impiety, then to aſſociate your ſelues to my aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, to betray my cauſe, to deny my reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and forſake the participation of my Sacraments. To haue more care of your ſubſtance, then of your ſoules, to poiſe the world and me in ballance, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre it before me; not to deale with my Prieſts, not to aſſemble at my praiers, to liue like Heathens, acknowledging the ſeruice which ye haunt to be folly and ſacrilege, yet otherwiſe wanting al
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:16437:40"/> exerciſe of Religion? Curſed is hee that doth my worke negligently and fraudulently, and curſed is he which doth it not al.</p>
            <p>Why doe I thus reprehend a ſort of innocents,<note place="margin">36. Excuſes of Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes refel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</note> who wiſh wel to me and my faith, and with al their hartes, deſire the returne of their fore-fathers daies, hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping my diſtreſſed members to their vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt power. It is not they which haue denied my faith, and aboliſhed my lawes; or which perſecute with ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity. What they doe, is againſt their wil vpon meere compulſion, not ſo much for regard of their owne particular, as of children and family, neither from the hart, but for faſhion ſake and obedience, and only for a time. They purpoſe not to die otherwiſe, then graffed into my body Myſtical, and true members of my Church, and in the meane ſpace re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme the time of their ſinne, vvith workes of mercy.</p>
            <p>Can iniquity thus teach your mouthes an vntrought? Pyned conſciences, howe greedily they pray vpon the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:16437:41"/> foode of falſhood. The bread of lying relliſheth wel in your taſt, but the grauel thereof ſhal grate your mouthes, and fret your mawes: Againſt your owne ſoules ye pleade.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">37. Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes are not excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of helping the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike.</note>Others indeede made the breach in <hi>Peters</hi> Net, but why haue ye with them fallen head-long forth? others ouer-ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the cockle, but why are ye choaked there-with? others raiſed the ſmoke, but how hapneth it that your eies are blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? others purſue and aſſault my Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, but why haue ye through your departure vveakened them, and made them a pray, to whom if ye had manfully ſtoode, neither they ſhould haue beene ſo oppreſſed, nor you liue in ſuch ſlauery of conſcience, nor I haue beene ſo diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured in this Realme, and almoſt quite exiled. What tel ye me of your ſimple aſſiſtance, which is the leaſt that ye ought to doe, but farre from the moſt that ye might. Is your continuance in Schiſme to further the conuerſion of England? What? Shal my Church be reared in iniquity, and Syon founded vpon dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:16437:41"/> ſoules? Can not I maintaine my power without your ſinnes? or (though I vſe you as I finde you) wil I euil that good may redounde thereof? I ſeeke not your goods, but your good; not your ſubſtance, but your ſanctification; you and not yours. Build not your ſinnes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my backe, for I wil caſt you head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long; I neede not your diſſimulation, you are not neceſſary to me at al. If I feede you without other mens aide, ſo can I feede others without you. Perhaps I am beholding vnto you, that ye are not ſuch flat Heretikes as ſome are, I had as liefe ye were. Oh we are luke warme; I would ye were cold: oh vve doe not wholy follow <hi>Baal.</hi> If <hi>Baal</hi> be God fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him wholy; if I be God, follow him not at al, but me: halt no longer betweene both. And what is it that ye dreame off, your good vvorkes?<note place="margin">38. Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit not glory not remi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſio by the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> good workes.</note> and frame imaginations of I know not what manner to redeeme your ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Pretend ye to be Chriſtians, to be of vnderſtanding, to know wel what ye doe, and are ignorant that al workes done in
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:16437:42"/> ſtate of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inne, and out of grace, how much ſoeuer they tend to piety, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend my honour, are aboundantly rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, if in conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>deration thereof I tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally bleſſe you, with health, wealth, or other pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>perity: ſeing they neither ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie my juſtice, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> merit remiſſion of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences. Hauing diſmembred the vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of my Church, by your departure, and violated the ſacred bond of her peace and charity, whatſoeuer ye doe, though ye gaue al to the poore, and your bodies to the fire for my ſake, ye are nothing, ye doe nothing, ye ſhal reape nothing. I ſpit at your workes, if you thinke that done out of grace, they ſerue to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Nothing ſaueth but by liuely vertue, and force of my Paſſion, vvith which none can haue affinity, who haue by ſinne made themſelues dead, deteſtable are ſuch in my ſight, vntil by profound and perfect repentance, they be reconciled to my fauour. No vvorkes are holy, where the ſoule is not ſanctified, no branch can beare fruit, except it bide in
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:16437:42"/> the ſtocke, cleanſe your veſſels, then put in your wine, and your floore before you heape corne. Ere vp a freſh your ground &amp; caſt not away your ſeede vpon thornes. My Church is a Vine, whereof I am the roote; become branches of this Vine, and then may ye beare fruit to ſaluation, keepe perfectly my Commandements,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.</note> and then haue confidence.</p>
            <p>Out of my ſight vvith polluted and blinde Sacrifices: away with the workes which ſmel of the contaminated caske. Abhominable are the offrings of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked;<note place="margin">Pro. 15.</note> neither wil I be greſed with the oile of ſinners, ſuch as the die is, ſuch is the coulour: ſuch as the pipe is, ſuch is the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor. Ye holy? your very juſtice and righteouſeſt actions are as ragges of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; the choiſeſt of you is but as chaffe, the ſmootheſt a Thiſtel, the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt is a Bryer, and the hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt among you an Hypocrite. Ye rich in merits? ye are vvretched, poore, miſerable, vvhen your heape (ſuch as it is) ſhal come to the Mil, ye ſhal finde that your graines were hollow and worme-eaten, fuller
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:16437:43"/> of filth then pure flowre. Wel voide, to the voide, and ful to the ful, they which haue, ſhal haue more and abound, and from you ſhal bee taken that little which ye haue. I wil ſuffer you to haue your courſe: ye are cold, but ye ſhal waxe colder: ye are runne farre from me, but ye ſhal runne further, I wil puffe away your almeſſe as aſhes, your giftes I wil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject as from diſſembling friends. I weene ye meaſure me by your ſelues, and thinke to bribe me before the day of judgement, your expectation ſhal be deceiued, and your ſinnes argued before al the world. What ſhal I doe vvith a multitude of your praiers, the lip-labour of defiled mouthes, and flattery of faithleſſe harts? Let not the confidence of them ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelme you,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 15.</note> 
               <hi>my</hi> praiſe is not fitting in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mouthes of ſinners, and execrable is his praier,<note place="margin">Pro. 28.</note> which wil not heare my law. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute not me, Lord, Lord, except ye fulfil my wil. If blaſphemous tongues can magnifie me a-right, then ſhal your mouthes perhaps praiſe me worthily; whoſe deedes blaſpheme me, I heare not
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:16437:43"/> ſinners.</p>
            <p>What magnifie you your faſtes exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,<note place="margin">Ioh. 9.</note> 
               <note place="margin">39. Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe in ſmaller matters neglect the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt.</note> neglecting the ſolemne and great faſt internal, from ſinne and wickednes? Your faſtes are infected with ſelfe wil, (in following your owne deſires and not mine) with worldly feare, with hatred of correction, and reprehenſion with fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward auerſion from the truth, with dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinne, what of your feaſtes, holy-daies, and other auncient obſeruances, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you chooſe what ye liſt, and what ye liſt ye contemne? ye faſt the Eues and keepe Holy-daies, poſſibly more then ordinary, in diſcerning of meates, many of you are more preciſe then you neede. But to communicate through feare with Heretikes in their ſacrilege; to abſtaine altogether from my Sacraments through feare, to deny me before men, is no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſcruple. Oh Pharaſees which ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry preciſely tith-mint and rue, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning whoſoeuer ſwarueth one jot from his duty, or doth not more then he is bound in theſe ſmaller matters, and brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king freely the maine precepts and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:16437:44"/> points of my commandement: Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites. Theſe greater thinges ought by any meanes ſtrictly to be obſerued; and then are the other not to be omitted. Firſt obſerue the ſubſtantial part, then haue care of ſecondary reſpects: Firſt, hold faſt ſurely the poſſeſſion and profeſſion of your faith: then neglect not the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies thereto belonging. Why ſtraine ye a Gnat, and ſwallow a Camel, feare a Mote and dread not a Beame, ſtoppe at a Straw, and ſtagger not at a Streame? To whom, but to ſuch as you did. I cry by my Prophet,<note place="margin">Ierem. 14.</note> that when they faſt and pray, I wil not heare them, and when they lift vp their handes, I wil turne away my face.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">40. The obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience refelled.</note>Let not the bare name of obedience blind-fold you. I forbidde you not to giue vnto Caeſar, that which is Caeſars, but deny me not mine. No, not though Caeſar would arrogate to himſelfe, that vvhich appertaineth to me. Yeeld to Caeſar goodes, life, al temporal ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, as farre as behoueth to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries commodity and regiment. Render
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:16437:44"/> to me a pure hart, and ſincere obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance vvithout al exception, this I challenge as my right. Honour the Prince for my ſake, but honour me for my ſelfe. So I ſay, Honour me, Feare me, Loue me, Reuerence me, Obey me, Serue me, which of you wil indure, that his Sonne ſhal diſobey him, and for his excuſe, that he did it by your ſeruants commandement? ye muſt not obey my ſeruant againſt me the Maſter, neither my Magiſtrate againſt me the Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord of al.</p>
            <p>Be ye your owne judges in this caſe, whether ye ought moſt to obey man or me: Goe ye to heretical conuenticles for obedience to the law? More tollerable ſhal it be at my great day to them, which yeeld of frailty and feare, not aggrauating their offence, by acknowledging prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue ouer ſoules, beſides that alone which I haue appropriated to my Church and ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es; neither joyning their exteriour ſchiſme with inward ſchiſme and hereſie. If obedience be a pretious thing performe it to me, to whom al ſubjection is due, and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:16437:45"/> to whom al powers bow, I command o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to ſuperiour preeminence, but not in derogation of my owne preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, neither am I contrary to my ſelfe. Neither muſt the law of the ſupreame Court, giue place to a meaner ſeate, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my celeſtial Throne, to a terrene Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal. What obedience is that, wherein is the greateſt diſobedience poſſible? what dutiful ſubjection, where in is moſt noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and perfidious rebellion? If the name of obedience be holy, whatſoeuer it pretendeth, and that againſt the ſilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles thereof, no reaſon can be heard, then obey the body commanding againſt the ſpirit, the world againſt heauen, the Deuil againſt me.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">41. The excuſe of feare rejected.</note>What now, if ye be not ſo madde as to allege that you ſinne againſt my law, by way of obedience, to the lawes of the Realme; but that what you doe of any goodneſſe, ye doe for loue of me, and that which ye omit, ye omit for feare of the world. Nay, what if al the good ye doe, be done for feare of my wrath, or for vaine-glory, and not for my loue? and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:16437:45"/> that which ye doe not, ye omit for loue of the world, preferring the ſame before my feare? for how can ye feare the world, but that ye loue too much the world, and feare leaſt it ſhould not loue you? Why ſtand ye in awe of her frowne, but becauſe ye would allure her fawne? you would not dread her bended browes, if her ſmile pleaſed you not too wel, and tickled not your hartes with delight. If you loathed the world, and could brooke either the abſence of her company, or the eie of her diſpleaſure, ye would not feare what ſhee could doe vnto you, which to ſpeake the moſt, is but to vſe you frowardly, or to baniſh you her ſight. This if ſhee did, am not I preſently ready with armes diſplai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to receiue you into my boſome, into my Pallace, into my eternal and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Tabernacles? If ye loued me, ye would not ſo loue the world, ye would not ſo feare her: Seing ye violate my commandement, becauſe of her coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termande, how is it not manifeſt, that wherein you obey me, ye obey me for feare of my reuenging rodde, which alſo
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:16437:46"/> ye would ſoone treade vnder foote, if the world ſhould thither in like ſort extend her prohibition.</p>
            <p>Oh faithleſſe cowardes, and not faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful champions: oh Hares and not Men: oh patternes of puſillanimity, what auai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it you for excuſe, feare indeede (as you ſay) driue you from your duty? I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently denounced that ye ſhould not feare them, which kil the body, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deſtroy the ſoule; but me, who can caſt both body and ſoule into euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting flames. Haue I no way deſerued, that you ſhould ſuffer for me; Number the pricks of my ſharpe pearſing thornes, number the bloudy and renting ſtripes, receiued oueral my body, from the rage where of no part from the crowne, to the plate was free, if ye cannot number theſe being innumerable, conſider my fiue deepeſt woundes, conſider my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpightful death, and what I ſuffered for the redemption of al mankinde, for yours in particular amongſt the reſt. Or I pray you, if you ſuffer any thing for my ſake, is my future glory an vnworthy
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:16437:46"/> recompenſe. Am I a ſlow pay-maſter, or a poore Lord, not able to make you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends, or are ye richer then I, and can expect no juſt retribution? If now while ye are my enimies, I haue prouided you, and furniſht you vvith many neceſſary thinges, and ſuffer you to enjoy the fruites of my excellent vvorke-man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, the Earth and Skie; haue I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued nothing in ſtore, to gratifie my friendes.</p>
            <p>Giue credit to my wordes, I tel you that bleſſed and a thouſand times happy are they, which ſuffer perſecution and croſſes for my name ſake, and for their conſcience, for great is their reward in heauen. If perfect wiſdome were to be talked to vnperfect hartes, I vvould tel you how to endure for religion, is a thing which in ſo ample vviſe ſatisfieth, for humane negligences and former offences, combineth ſo ſingular a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land for the ſufferers; ſo exquiſitely conformeth to the type of my Paſſion, and maketh men ſo like to mee their Sauiour, that Saints in al ages haue
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:16437:47"/> with teares of harty affection deſired it; with joy imbraced it, drawing neare and feruently ſought it, when it was farre off: why feare ye and tremble (oh ye of little faith) why diſpaire ye, &amp; caſt your ſelues away, O ye of no faith? The ſhippe-man calleth to me from the bottome of the Sea, in expectation to be ſwallowed, and I heare him. The trauailer paſſing through the midſt of theeues craueth my a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, and I conduct him ſafe. <hi>Daniel</hi> was ſecure in the Lyons den. <hi>Ionas</hi> in the Whales belly, the three children in the furnace, becauſe I aſſiſted them. I forſooke not my Diſciples and ſhippe, though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time I ſeeme to ſleepe, and to forget them. If your eies were worthy to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, you ſhould ſee as my ſeruant <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeus</hi> did, millions of Angels in readineſſe for preſeruation of my Church and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. Feare not therefore, that from which both I can deliuer you if I wil, and wil as I ſee it beſt.</p>
            <p>Deny ye my omnipotency and ability to deliuer you; or if I cal you to ſuffer ſome-what for me, who are ye that dare
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:16437:47"/> detract and ſay, ye wil not, if ye be ſo bold, can ye aliue or dead eſcape my handes, but that I wil make you ſuffer euen in this life, much more for your ſinnes, and that without al conſolation, thankes, or recompence?</p>
            <p>That which ye feare ſhal come furiou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly vpon you, and oppreſſe you like an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Giant. Though ye feare to ſerue me, yet wil not I be afraide to repay your da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtardy, with a dreadful hire. The ſlouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful perſon feareth to be ſtoned with a peece of turfe, pretendeth for his lazines:<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 22.</note> 
               <hi>A Lyon is without the dore: in the midſt of the ſtreete I ſhal be deuoured.</hi> What aileſt thou Prophet of ſlouth, if thou take courage I am with thee.<note place="margin">Pro. 29.</note> Feare me and my law, he which feareth man, ſhal ſoone periſh; but he which truſteth in me ſhal be aſſured. What feareſt thou per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution as a Lyon: Feare ſinne and flie from it, for it is a Serpent, and a two ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſword. You heare not, you are not perſwaded: Goe your waies ye vnkinde wreatches; ye ſhal not ſuffer for me, for ye are not worthy.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:16437:48"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">42. Excuſe of neceſſity ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne.</note>Neceſſity you ſay hath no law; but deſerueth pardon. Oh how you vexe me with wilful blindneſſe. What ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity is there, why ye ſhould deny your faith by going to the malignant congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation? Neceſſity forceth you to ſaue your ſoules, for if ye doe not, in vaine ye haue receiued them, nay curſed is the houre vvherein ye were borne, vvho haue fruſtrated the end of your crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vvhich was that glorifying me in this life, ye might be glorified by me in the life to come, and cauſed my bloud to be ſhedde for you in vaine, and ſhal be damned for euer-more, without al re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
            <p>But no neceſſity compelleth you to ſaue your life, much leſſe your goodes. What if ye become poore, yea moſt poore? What if ye die? is not the cauſe mine? Is it not your faith that ye ſuffer for? I repeate it againe. No neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity conſtraineth you to ſaue your life, much leſſe your goodes; neither care of your ſelues; neither care of your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.</p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:16437:48"/>
            <p>Can not I prouide for you and yours,<note place="margin">43. Care of family is no excuſe of ſchiſme.</note> without your ſinne? Aske the Birdes, Fiſhes, and Beaſtes, who feedeth them, vvhereas they neither ſow nor reape. Say not with the murmurers: <hi>Can God prouide vs foode in the deſert,</hi> feare their example, I gaue them ſuſtainance, and when they were not content with ſuch as I ſent, I condeſcended to them their hartes deſire, but while the meate was in their mouthes, my wrath fel vpon them. The expectation of the careful ſhal pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and the leſſe ye truſt in me,<note place="margin">Rom. 11.</note> the leſſe regard I wil haue of you. Seing you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>card me from your accompts, I diſcharge my ſelfe of your care. Wilt thou needes prouide for thy family? thou doeſt wel? doth natural loue inſtigate thee to ſeeke their maintainance? So doe I alſo, yea I tel thee, if thou feele not this inſtinct, thou art vvorſe then an Infidel. But how behoueth it thee to prouide? by hooke and by crooke, by ſinne, Schiſme, Infidelity, Perjury, Theft, Murther? muſt al things be lawful to thee for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainance of thy family, according to thy
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:16437:49"/> calling? Or muſt thou prouide for them only by induſtry, labour, or any other honeſt and juſt meanes; and touching the reſt, commit them to me? My com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements doe not one impugne the other, neither haue I willed any man to offend.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 15.</note>When I commanded to loue me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue al, did I except wife and children? did I not peremptorily auouch, that he is vnworthy of me, whoſoeuer preferreth them in any thing before me? Curſed ſhal the child be, which ſhal be reſpected aboue me and my commandements; be he innocent, yet ſhal he ſuſtaine the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coile of his fathers iniquity. And he which taketh hold vpon the natural loue engraffed by me in your hartes, why doe ye not inferre with your ſelues, that if he who prouideth not for his family tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral neceſſaries, is worſe then an Infidel, he which neglecteth prouiſion for their ſoules, is a very Deuil: Vnleſſe ye thinke that the body is more pretious then the ſoule. But I aſſure you that al is loſt if the ſoule be loſt; ye ſhew wel therefore, that
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:16437:49"/> you loue your children for your owne ſakes and delight, and not for me or my wil, thus turning the law of nature, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me the authour of nature. Goe forwardes ye vvho are ſo ſollicitous for your houſe-hold and poſterity, proceede in your cares; vvhen ye haue al done, both hazarded and loſt your ſoules, and daily offended me for their ſakes; who is it that foſtered and preſerued them? you or I? who filled their Mothers breſts with milke? who gaue to you that affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of loue, which maketh you to aſſiſt them?</p>
            <p>Tel me whoſoeuer thou be, which truſteſt more in thine owne ſollicitude, or (to ſpeake plainely) more diſtruſteſt me, then that thou dareſt commit them to my handes, canſt thou feede thy ſelfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my prouidence? I, who but I? che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh the younge Rauens, cloath the Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and Flowres, open my handes and fil al the earth with bleſſings, I number not the ſtarres only, but the very haires of your head, why then dare ye not rely vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my refuge.</p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:16437:50"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:16437:50"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:16437:51"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">44. The true cauſe why Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes going to Church are ripped.</note>I haue laide before you the excuſes, which the beſt of you with vnſacred lips, and vncircumciſed hart doe forge. Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and vnſearchable is mans minde, but I vvho am the ſearcher of hartes, wil finde out euery corner. The reede on vvhich you leane, ſhal runne through your handes and breake. Are theſe your cauſes and pretexts? Pretexts they are, but not cauſes. He eaſily findeth occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which wil needes breake friendſhip. If you wil not vtter the very cauſe, but are aſhamed thereof; then heare it at leaſt, and confeſſe a truth. Charity is waxen cold in your hartes, the world or the fleſh haue ouer-whelmed you, ye want ſaith; of the Catholike beleefe, you haue no certainty, as infallible; but opinion only, that is probable.</p>
            <p>Your ſoules are ouer-growne vvith ſinnes and ſenſualites, as a barren field with buſhes and brambles; your corrupt affection tieth you more ſtrongly to the world, then if you were chained by one foote to a ſtake, you can not ſoare aloft, not lift vp your hartes to congitation of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:16437:51"/> celeſtial and ſpiritual thinges. If ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ye caſt vp as it were one eie to heauen, ye cannot but fixe the other on earth; if ye proffer vp one foote, the other is faſt clogde; ye cannot moue, if ye offer to vſe the triple winges of grace, reaſon, and free-wil: the maſſy poiſe of fleſh and bloud abaſeth you preſently, before ye can make winge. Ye vvil ſuffer nothing, ye wil looſe nothing, ye wil beare no paine, ſuſtaine no detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, incurre no diſgrace, indure no calamity, ye wil diminiſh no diet, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach no ſleepe, abate no part of your port, impaire no credit, abridge no li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, caſt off no ſuperfluity.</p>
            <p>Ye little thinke,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.</note> that to ſerue me is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect liberty, to looſe for me is great gaines: it commeth not to your minde, that a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure conſcience is a continual banquet, and that the fruit of a religious hart, is joy and peace. What ſhal I doe to ſuch a nice, delicate, and vnmortified generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? If the times were good, could ye ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily goe to heauen: not ſo ſoone as ye ſuppoſe. Ye vvil neuer take vp my
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:16437:52"/> Croſſe and follow me, who when I lay it vpon you, and help you to beare it, thruſt it from you with violence, and hurle it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with a miſchiefe. Let your ſainting hartes meditate defence of their conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: but they ſhal not be innocent. Build pretence while you wil, but ye ſhal not be guarded from the tempeſt of my wrath. Waſh your ſelues with ſope, as long as ye liſt, ye ſhal neuer be cleane: Why being inuited to my heauenly banquet, deſire ye to be holden excuſed? Why ſay ye that ye cannot come: what neede theſe complements? Speake plainely, ſay as the truth is; ſay, <hi>we wil not come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh fie, ſuch wordes to our Lord God? ſuch a flat denial to our maker?<note place="margin">45. Againſt ſuch as or defer their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſion.</note> 
               <hi>Nay, Spare vs a while O Father of heauen, we wil but ſet thinges in order, and waight a conuenient time, at leaſt once before we die, we wil approch to thy ſanctified Table.</hi> Craue you then daies and deliberation? Is it for my behoofe or your commodity, I inuite you? Need I your ſaluation, more then of ſo many other ſoules, Iewes, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels, and others, which I hourely ſuffer
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:16437:52"/> to periſh, and inuite them not to life? whom if I inuited, I ſhould finde multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of them, anſwerable to my inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and if I had giuen them ſome few of thoſe opportunities &amp; motiues, which I afforded to you, they would long ſince haue done penance in ſack-cloath and aſhes, and beene conuerted perfectly from their wicked waies. Or if beſides my Quyres of Angels and Saints, I yet would be glorified of more, can I not create more children to <hi>Abraham?</hi> or when ye haue done your beſt, haue ye not beene vnanſwerable to your talents as vnprofitable ſeruants? Did I chooſe you firſt, or did you chooſe me? I choſe you and loued you, before ye were in nature, before ye were any thing, and now ye be ſome-thing ye forſake me. And yet though ye haue forſaken me, I haue not ſo forſaken you, but that I inuite you once more to returne. Turne vnto me, and I wil turne vnto you. Nay, behold I turne vnto you, turne therefore vnto me, I humble my ſelfe to ſeeke firſt the attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; I inuite you gratis to my ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminent
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:16437:53"/> glory. Aske any man if he wil intreate you, or hire you to partake of his bleſſings: yet behold I inuite you.</p>
            <p>Come, come, my children, come poore ſoules, take your fil for thankes, not Wine and Milke or Honny, but of ſupernal, immortal, and Angelical foode, vvhich who ſo eateth, liueth for euer, and who ſo eateth not, can haue no life in him. Come, and ye ſhal not only be wel-come, but I wil giue you preſent grace, as pledge of future glory, I wil giue you remiſſion of ſinne, I wil make you one with me, I wil endew you with ſome eſpecial fauour. For I am not he that enter any where and am wel enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, but I there bountifully leaue my remembrance. If euer I deſerued wel at your handes, if euer ye expect any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pleaſure, if ye loue me, if ye ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour me, if ye feare me; come, delay I may not beare. My fatlings and fowle are killed, al thinges are in readineſſe, and I wil not ſtay. If ye wil not come for my ſake, come for your owne.</p>
            <p>Come while you are in health: For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:16437:53"/> the world before it forſake you, This is merit and thankes. Come while your ſenſes ſerue, vvhile your wits are your owne, while as reaſonable you may vſe reaſon, before ye be drowſie and ſpeachleſſe as beaſts, or rauing as dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſpirits.</p>
            <p>Come quickly, leaſt ye be taken in a trappe, at an houre vnlookt for, and neuer come; or at leaſt vvhen you vvould, no meanes occurre; vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ye cannot come. Bring forth the vvriting, vvherein I haue indented with you, not to cal you til ye be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; if you haue any deede or leaſe of life or yeares, ſhew me my ſeale, and then build vpon my aſſurance. If you haue no ſuch, ſhew me at leaſt ſome parrol vvarrant; if ye hold on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at vvil; why dally you, vvhy delay you? Why preuent ye not my ſodaine ſummons, hauing no Charter of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate?</p>
            <p>Oh miſerable ſoules, vvhoſe chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt hope is, that vvhich of al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinges is next to damnation, the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:16437:54"/> moſt horrible? that is to be conuerted a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the end of your life; then which, what is more perilous or vncertaine?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">46. Againſt thoſe which ſay the Prince ſhal an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere.</note>There are among you, which are not yet ſo forward, as to purpoſe to turne to me at their laſt houre; but can finely ſhift themſelues from the ſeuerity of my judgement, although they acknowledge their actions to be il. They can ſhunne the blame thereof vpon the Prince and the law-makers, who are the cauſes of their ſinne. Your ſoules indeede I vvil require at their handes, but what is that to you, who per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh in your iniquities. What may the puniſhment of the acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary auaile the principal felon? of juſt actions, the motiue is not reproueable, not the cauſe il, if your act be not dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, what is their offence. Are ye In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants? or wil ye pleade ſimplicity? or are ye men who becauſe their free-wil cannot be forced further, then they liſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, are at their owne peril to looke to their doings. The theefe alleageth his neceſſity, the fornicatour the violence of his paſſion you the terrour of the lawes?
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:16437:54"/> Aſwel you might al thinke your ſelues excuſed, by caſting the fault vpon the Deuil, who tempreth you.</p>
            <p>Loe here the weakeneſſe of your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications? Either you goe for obedience, or compelled for feare, or for loue of your family: either you lay the fault vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on others, or you deferre your conuerſion. Scar-bugs and viſards to terrifie children, not to amaze men; excuſes to mocke fooles, not to ſatisfie him which requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth reaſon.</p>
            <p>Are theſe the bulwarkes that muſt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine the day of my wrath?<note place="margin">47. Excuſe of Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes how vaine and weake.</note> are theſe your trenches for time of battaile? If Spiders webs can with-hold the Eagles flight; if a thinne boorde can recoile the roring Canon, then ſhal theſe allegations ſerue for a good plea. Souldiers truſt not in gilded armour, nor the marriner in painted ſhippes. Dare ye venture your ſoules on ſuch friuoulous illuſions? you may deceiue others, you may deceiue your ſelues, but me ye cannot deceiue; no not though you thinke to ouer-reach me, and perſwade me to be content:
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:16437:55"/> I ſee not as man ſeeth, for man ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeth, but nothing eſcapeth my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, yet if as man I ſee; what man is ſo blinde that ſeeth not your diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and offence? I wil waigh al your actions euen to a graine, and keepe tale of al your ſinnes euen to one; I wil rippe vp your hartes, diſcouer the center of your cogitations, and lay open your bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren rootes, your adulterate loue I reject; your fained obedience I renounce; your pretended deſerts I caſt out off my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 11.</note>There is a vvay which ſeemeth to a man not to be vnrighteous, and the end thereof leadeth to death: Such is the courſe which you enſue. There is a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration which ſeemeth pure to it ſelfe, and is not cleanſed from her filth:<note place="margin">Pro. 30.</note> ſuch a generation are ye. But (as I told you before) the reaſon hereof is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe vanity bewitcheth you, obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that which is beſt, and peruerting your vnderſtanding.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.</note> Becauſe judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is not out of hand pronounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, therefore ye ſecurely wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:16437:55"/> in ſinne: ye loue your ſelues and not me. Selfe-loue I ſay you haue, for indeece ye loue not rightly your ſelues, if ye did, ye vvould loue me more then your ſelues.<note place="margin">Tob. 12.</note> Hee that loueth ſinne, is the Enimy of his owne ſoule.</p>
            <p>What ſhal I ſay to you?<note place="margin">48. Againſt thoſe which appeal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mercy.</note> though al excuſes faile you, yet wil you not faile to excuſe, when nothing ſerueth your turne, then appeale you to my mercy, Appeale to my mercy when ye harty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repent, not while ye purpoſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in ſinne; vvhile ye liue, not when ye be dead; while ye be yet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, not vvhen ye be apprehended, and caſt into priſon for my debt, I am merciful. Now come to mee, and I wil take you to mercy. Wil ye not come? Then in calling mee merciful ye mocke me.<note place="margin">Exod. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> To ſay <hi>the Lord is righteous, and we are wicked,</hi> ſhal no more auaile you, then it did <hi>Pharao,</hi> except ye forſake your iniquity. Shal a Man for-giue his Wife, if ſhee perſiſt ſtil in her
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:16437:56"/> adulterous minde, or his Sonne if he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue his contempt? if ſuch may be found yet wil not I be ſo fond. Oh deſperate boldneſſe: Becauſe my word extolleth my mercy, and examples of my clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy are maruailous, in confidence thereof to waxe male part and bold, and to tel me before hand, that preſuming there-vpon, you wil neither care what you doe to me, nor what I ſay to you.</p>
            <p>Shal then the Arbiter of the heauens be vnjuſt, and the Iudge of Iudges be corrupted? Shal I ſo a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſe my ſelfe, as to abſolue whom the final verdict ſhal finde guilty? Then vvere my iniquity greater then yours. If ye hope to finde mercy, without conuerſion to the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of mercy, and auerſion from your wickedneſſe,<note place="margin">Pro. 10.</note> ye gape to feede vpon winde, and follow birdes flying in the aire, your hope is as thiſtle-downe, which euery breath ſcattereth. In this conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth my aboundant mercy, that I haue not al this while taken you away in the midſt of your ſinne, but patiently a long time put vp al abuſes, and expected you
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:16437:56"/> to repentance; that I haue louingly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen you diuers motiues of remorſe, that I haue by ſecret meanes remoued from you diuers occaſions of further ſinne, that I haue not ſuffered the enimy, to execute his malice againſt you, in ſuch ſort as he would haue done, and as ye deſerued; that yet alſo I am preſt to receiue you once more, euen now inuite you againe to ſaluation.</p>
            <p>As for the reſt, you haue heard (I am ſure) and by authority authentical, that I am a hard Lord, reaping where I ſowed not; a ſeuere creditour, that wil exact of vngrateful debtours the vttermoſt far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; a preciſe Iudge, which wil exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and cal to accompt euery idle word. A ſtraight Prince,<note place="margin">Math. 25</note> which wil damne to vtter darkeneſſe an vnprofitable ſeruant, a terrible God, vvhich for negligences and omiſſions of ſmaller matters, then exerciſe of religion and profeſſion of faith wil denounce: <hi>Goe ye curſed into euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting fire.</hi> Haue I not flatly proclaimed that the way to heauen is ſtraight, the gate narrow, and ſew ſhal enter; that
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:16437:57"/> ſcant the juſt ſhal be ſaued. If it ſhal goe ſo hard vvith good Catholikes, vvhat ſhal become of you? if the flouriſhing and fruitful tree ſhal ſcant eſcape fire, what ſhal the dry and vvithered ſtocke? This if ye wil not now vnderſtand to ſaluation, the tempter ſhal beate it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your heades, at your final houre to deſperation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">49. Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes rely vpon hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</note>My wordes I waſt, not able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade this wiſe and circumſpect compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, vvho caſt beyonde the Moone, and thinke vvith their farre reach to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe my prouidence, vvho deeme it a feate of the greateſt folly that may be, to venture goodes for grace, their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings for my loue; to hazard terrene honour, for hope of Celeſtial glory, and a little temporal proſperity, for eternal felicity. This is the ſumme of your reckoning. Firſt and principally, before the care of God and conſcience, I wil quietly enjoy my wealth, and liue in eſtimation among al men to my pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: Shal I be in danger of want, or ſeeke a ſtraungers table, vvho am now able
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:16437:57"/> to entertaine others? Shal my enimies haue aduantage ouer me, and treade me vnder feete? Shal varlets and ribauldes poſſeſſe themſelues of my ſubſtance, which I haue ſo painefully gotten toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo carefully kept? Shal I liue in priſon, and be vſed I know not how, who now may goe where I liſt, and ſport at my pleaſure?</p>
            <p>Vnderſtand what is true pollicy (oh ye babes) learne perfect prudence (oh ye fooles) that which you ſay is vanity; and the practiſe thereof is meere madde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.<note place="margin">Pro. 1. &amp;. 9.</note> The beginning of wiſdome (if your vviſdomes wil conſider it) is my feare,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.</note> and the accompliſhment of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is the awe of me. This is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and the end, this is al in al.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.</note> The wiſdome of the fleſh is fooliſhneſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me,<note place="margin">Pro. 12.</note> and the waies of the wicked ſhal finally deceiue them, ye ſay ye are not blinde; your owne wordes condemne ye,<note place="margin">Ioh. 9.</note> and of them I take witneſſe, that ye erre not of ſimplicity and ignorance. Beguile not your ſelues, I am not to be jeſted vvith al. Meaſure your fore-ſight,<note place="margin">Pro. 23.</note>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:16437:58"/> truſt not ouer-much to your deuiſes, which I wil bring to confuſion,<note place="margin">Pro. 3.</note> but haue confidence in me with al your hart. Be no longer wiſe in wickedneſſe, and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in goodneſſe: Seeke firſt the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uen, and the righteouſneſſe thereof, and al thinges elſe ſhal be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied by me.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> The wiſdome of the fleſh is death, but wiſdome of the ſpirit is life eternal. If ye abhorre to be a triumph to your enimies; Let not the Deuil the chiefeſt foe of al, braue me by the ſpoiles of your ſoules.</p>
            <p>Now you are captiue, now may your backe friendes ſcorne you, now doe they treade vpon you, when they haue made you yeeld vnto them, and for feare of them, to doe that which is both a ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſhift, and which they know vexeth you to the hart: For he is neuer ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come vvhich maketh reſiſtance, but he whoſe courage failing, recanteth as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creant. Neither is your eſtimation to be ſtoode vpon, as a matter of worth, for honeſty may be wel thought crackt, where Chriſtian duty to God hath taken
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:16437:58"/> her flight. It cannot be expected, that he wil be loyal to man, who hath violated fidelity to his maker. If you force not of this credit, but intend authority, gape af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dignity, loue ſuperiority, and delight to command, are not your hartes guilty of abhominable ambition, and teſtifie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, that ye loue the honour of men, more then the honour of your Lord God? Let your glory be to know me; for to follow me is perfect worſhip.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 23.</note> I am the glory of my people, and they are my countenance.</p>
            <p>Liberty you loue; why then remaine ye the ſlaues of ſinne? ye are content to be the Deuils bond men and thral, rather then ye wil be my ſeruants; and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure his heauy fetters, rather then ſuſtaine my ſweet yoke. Vſe the liberty which I haue giuen you, captiuate not your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and free-wil, to the earthly inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſenſuality. And why ſhould you preferre gold and ſiluer before me, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I redeemed not you with corruptible mettel, but with the laſt droppe of my bloud? The earth is mine,<note place="margin">Luke 15.</note> ye are mine
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:16437:59"/> husband-men and labourers; al goodes are mine, and ye are my Stewardes; is it much for you to render to me my owne, if I demande it? you are rich enough, if ye haue a good conſcience;<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.</note> and moſt peſtilent pouerty is in a wicked breaſt, vvherein is no goodneſſe. Better is piety then pretious ſtones,<note place="margin">Pro. 30.</note> it is the word of life; and a Bay-tree alwaies flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.<note place="margin">Rom. 15. Eccleſ. 27.</note> Better is a little with piety, then great treaſures. Many ſeeking riches, turne away their ſight from ſeing truth, and eaſily make ſhipvvracke of their ſoules; ſeeke not ſo eagerly, that which is an impediment to the entry of my Kingdome.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">50. The great folly of Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes.</note>But for aſmuch as you thinke your ſelues ſo wiſe, conſider yet a little, and you ſhal ſee much more of your fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which euery child may plainely diſcry, and conuict you of folly; what profiteth it you, that my Church hath power to forgiue ſinnes, ſeing you haue no acceſſe vnto it? that ſhee prayeth for her children, both liue and dead, ſeing ye be none of hers?</p>
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:16437:59"/>
            <p>What auaileth it you, that my Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is a medicine to ſaluation, ſeing ye apply it not vnto you? that my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Body ſanctifieth and prepareth to glory, ſeing ye neuer receiue it? What booteth it you, that the juſt ſhal ſhine like the Sunne, ſeing ye for your ſchiſme, ſhal be as vgly as fiendes? that to the righteous is prepared a Kingdome of glory; ſeing ye be vvicked, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue torment in Hel? That there is a Heauen, ſeing ye ſhal not enter into it. Angels and Saints, ſeing ye ſhal neuer enjoy their company?</p>
            <p>Finally, in vaine it is to you that there is a God, into whoſe reſt ye ſhal neuer enter, and whoſe face ye ſhal neuer ſee, ye haue mouthes, and praiſe me not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right; eares, but neuer heare the Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical praiers, and voice of my Spouſe, eies ye haue, and neuer behold me your Sauiour, though moſt louingly I offered my pretence among men, that they may daily remember my Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:16437:60"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">50. God wil peruert the wiſdome of Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matikes.</note>Al this notwithſtanding you thinke your ſelues wiſe, and that my Catholikes are improuident perſons. Contend with them no longer, but contend with me. See if I turne not your deuiſes againſt your ſelues, and make the wicked fruits of your vaine conceipts, to light vpon your owne heades. Contend with me in wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ſee whether you can more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily lay a foundation of felicity, or I ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert it; you gather together, or I ſcatter; you purpoſe, or I preuent; you deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, or I fruſtrate. Your truſt is in the ſecurity, which is promiſed and permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto you, for your vnconſcionable conformity; as though they could aſſure you of proſperity.</p>
            <p>Curſed is the man, which truſteth in man: Whence ye leaſt feare danger, I ſend out miſchiefe againſt you as a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant, and my wrath as a Purſuiuant, no ſtrength ſhal be able to defend you, nor any place to hide you. I would haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered you from them, but who ſhal reſcue wretched ſinners out of my hands. I diſpiſe ſuch, as to pleaſe men diſpleaſe
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:16437:60"/> me, and their bones I wil cruſh a ſunder. As I hate the ring-leaders and maſters of falſhood, ſo abhorre I their diſciples and confederates: You feare them, but it is I which wil plague you; you dread to ſtep in the hoare froſt, but ſnow ſhal ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelme you; ye feare drops, but ſtormes ſhal ouer-take you; ye feare a cracke as it were of thunder, but I wil ſtrike you with my horrible boltes in deede. As with the holy I am holy, ſo vvith the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thwart I wil be ouer-thwart, of al the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil which you haue ſowen, ye ſhal reape ſeauen-fold; for to the ſword I haue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained thoſe,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 16.</note> who paſſe from righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the Tents of iniquity,<note place="margin">Iud. 5.</note> Anathema to the land of Meror, for not aiding my Iſraelites in their extremity of battaile, and Anathema to thoſe, whoſe joyning with my aduerſaries, and yeelding to them, hath made my hoſt a pray, yet want I not meanes to maintayne my Church, and without you it ſhal triumph.</p>
            <p>Vnprofitable trees, how long ſhal I expect fruit in vaine? yeares and yeares are paſſed, and alwaies I finde you barren.
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:16437:61"/> The Axe therefore ſhal be ſet to your rootes, and ye ſhal ſerue for fire, if ye were Roſes as ye be cankers, yet being ſo intangled among thornes and briers, ye ſhould goe together to the ſurnace, ye ſhal ſee my Catholikes in my King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and your ſelues be kept without dores as dogges; which of my Saints wil ſtand betweene you and my fury, whoſe communion you haue renounced, with whoſe impugners ye are aſſociate.</p>
            <p>What helpe can ye hope for of the Angels, whom ye haue contriſtated by auerſion from their King? Your Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian Angels ye haue chaſed away, by entring Schiſmatical Temples. They are aſhamed to haue laboured ſo long in vaine about you, neither wil follow you into the Kingdome of darkeneſſe. At that day therefore, ye ſhal ſee my children gliſtering in glory, and ſhal ſay. <hi>Behold theſe are they, whoſe courſe of life we eſteemed ridiculous, and zeale to be meere madneſſe, whom we thought to be miſerable, and eſchewed their company as ful of calamity, now with how great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:16437:61"/> hath God deuided their felicity from our wreatchedneſſe?</hi> If I deferre til then you care not. Nay, the Iudge is at the gate, and his rodde ſleepeth not; Though ye be flexible by fauour, yet wil I be juſt, though ye diſſemble with me, I wil not diſſemble with you, nor faile of my threatning word. Ye ſhal know that I looke not downe on earth for nothing, nor in vaine behold the actions of the Sonnes of men. Ye doubt whether there by prouidence, but when I repay you in waight and meaſure, and ſubuert al your wiſe imaginations, then ye ſhal feele it.</p>
            <p>Goe to the Synagogues of Sathan, ſit with the malignant in their Church, and wot wel that you ſhal be judged for ſo doing. Paſſe this life as merrily as you can, but hope not for the life to come. Be not content with your owne euil, but peruert and hinder others alſo, (which is the proper office of the Deuil) rather then further them to ſaluation as Angels. Ye ſhal one day finde, that double ſinnes are needleſſe, for of one you ſhal be condemned. Feare of diſgrace
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:16437:62"/> ſpurreth you to perdition, forgetting that I gaue <hi>Toby</hi> fauour in the ſight of King <hi>Salmanaſar,</hi> aboue al others, becauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue al others he honoured me moſt, and leaſt ſeared the Kinges diſpleaſure, in matter of conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Ioſeph</hi> might alſo ſerue you of example, that credit is not alway loſt by ſeruing of me, but ſeing ye ſo feare to looſe mens fauour, ye ſhal looſe it, they ſhal maligne you, abuſe you, hate you worſe then Recuſants. From your wealth and fatneſſe proceedeth often your ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, I wil make you leaner, multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your miſeries, and the third heire ſhal neuer enjoy thoſe thinges, for enjoying whereof ye forſake me. I wil put a ring in your noſtrels, and a curbe in your mouthes, your owne conceipts ſhal pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and my wil ſhal preuaile. You are jealous of your honours, and thinke you that I wil not ſtand vpon mine. Becauſe you diſpiſe me, I therefore defie you; and as ſpittle I caſt you out of my mouth. You are none of mine, and I wil be none of yours; I wil blot you out, and croſſe
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:16437:62"/> you as notes out of vſe are wiped out of tables. And when I behold your neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, I wil clappe my handes ouer you. You haue caſt me away as a burthenſome and vnprofitable God. But I wil ſhake you off, as a man would caſt filth from his coate. Ye haue ſet a time to your ſelues, beyond which ye wil not expect, and now tired with expectation, ye are quite deſperate. Me, who made the globles of heauen, wil ye limit? to me who am e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, wil ye preſcribe an houre or a yeare? For this marke what I tel you; ye that ſay, <hi>We ſhal neuer ſee good daies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 14,</note> 
               <hi>but ſhal die in the wilderneſſe, and therefore now let vs follow the time.</hi> Good times ſhal come, and ye ſhal neuer ſee them, but die in the wilderneſſe, and (which is worſe) in your ſinne; your fortune ſhalbe like to the incredulous captaine, who ſaw the wonderful plenty and alteration,<note place="margin">4. Reg. 7.</note> which he beleeued ſhould come to paſſe, but neuer enjoyed the benefit thereof, and ye likewiſe which ſay. <hi>Good time ſhal ſhortly come, we wil not be to forward before we ſee them, but wil then be conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:16437:63"/> Good time ſhal come vvhen I appoint: the prefixed number of my Martirs being accompliſhed, when al hartes haue beene ſufficiently laide open, when I haue tried out, and retried al diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblers, ſuch as I finde you to be: Yet ſhal not the fruit hereof, nor the joy be ſuch, as you promiſe to your ſoules, ſome of you ſhal die before, others at that time, vvhen they would moſt gladly liue a while, others ſhal euen then haue their hartes hardened in ſome other ſinne, as now in Schiſme.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">52. An inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to returne from ſinne.</note>Repent therefore, repent and turne to the Sheepe-heard of your ſoules: O ye my ſheepe; turne vnto your Lord God O ye children, why ſet ye your ſoules to ſale for vanity, and ſel your ſelues to the Deuil for a vile price? Why ſuffer ye creatures to draw you from your Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour? Adhere no more to gold, ſiluer, and poſſeſſions, vvhere-with I often cloy my ſlaues, and ſmile at your childiſhneſſe. Let not droſſy mucke, nor dirty farmes ſeperate you any longer from my church. Wed not your ſelues ſo ſtraightly to the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:16437:63"/> world, which paſſeth in a moment, and al that is therein, no otherwiſe then a cloude before the Sunne.</p>
            <p>The riches that ye haue, others had before, and ſome muſt haue after you. Aske your Mannours and Landes, how many owners th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y haue had, and they vvil reckon vp vnto you a long Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue; none of whom could euer yet by wit, ſtrength, or power, either retaine them ſtil himſelfe, or aſſure them to his poſterity, ye ſhal finde them bought, ſold, changed, reexchanged, giuen, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herited, purchaſed, let out, morgaged, forfeited, vſurped, conquered, loſt, recouered, by right, by wrong, by might, by law, with a thouſand other alterations. If the ſundry liues, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanure of ſuch ſeueral poſſeſſors, and what theſe goodes did cauſe vnto them, were recorded. Ye ſhould ſee ſubſtance and poſſeſſions to be nothing elſe, but the pray of extortioners, the object of ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenours, the eie-ſore of great perſonages, the ready pray of a Tyrant, the nourſe of vnthriftineſſe, the wracke of youth,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:16437:64"/> the carke of age, the ſource of al vice, the ſhipwracke of al ſoules: A but then, which oppreſſeth al that vndertake it, a gate out of which enuy cannot be ſhut forth, a thorny buſh which choaked al goodneſſe and grace. Regard them not therefore, but haue pitty on your ſoules, ſpare your ſelues and ſinne no more.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 30.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Returne, O my prodigal children, and I wil receiue you. How many h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings haue their fil in my houſe, while ye in a forraigne land deuour huskes with ſwine. Returne, and I wil cladde you with a new ſtole, and caſt your ſinnes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the bottome of the Sea. Let euery one of you haſten to ſaue himſelfe, as being in a daungerous tempeſt, to him which doth periſh, al the world periſheth. Why die you and liue not? Why ſpend you your talents, and not in purchaſing heauen? Circumciſe your hartes, that ye may vnderſtand, pul your tailes out of your eares, and ſtoppe not reaſon with ſenſuality: ye are not beaſts but men, vſe the dignity of ſoules, of reaſon, of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, of free-wil. Follow me in ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:16437:64"/> of hart, and proue me if I ſhew not my ſelfe a good God vnto you and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I wil forſake you, or yet ſuffer you to be tempted aboue your power, or any further then is neceſſary for your good, you ſhal ſee that nothing is better then to feare me, and nothing ſweeter then my law; yea,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 23. Eccleſ. 1.</note> I wil prouide for you by ſuch meanes, as you would leaſt expect. So ſhal ye be ſure to taſt happineſſe at laſt, and to be bleſſed at your end.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 2. Eccleſ. 24.</note> No man euer truſted in me and was deluded. Be not aſhamed to defend truth and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it. For this confuſion wil bring you to glory.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 4.</note> Be not a-fraide to ſtriue euen vnto death for righteouſneſſe, I am your reward incomprehenſible.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 17.</note> Paſſe to the part of the holy flocke and liue with them, which liue and praiſe my name.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 21.</note> The Synagogue of ſinners is as a heape of ſtubble, and their end is a flame. What reward is it to be Catholikes, when times are Catholike,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 18.</note> now in the time of impiety and infidelity, ſhew a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation. With-draw your ſelues from thoſe, whom malice and ſinne hath
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:16437:65"/> blinded, depart from their pollution, touch not their filthineſſe, away from it, away from it; come not neare it on paine of your ſoules. Looke backe to the rocks from which ye haue fallen; for bleſſing is vpon Syon, and curſe vpon Hebal; my ſpirit ouer Hieruſalem, and my ſword o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Babylon: Become ye fellow Citizens of the Saints; enrole your ſelues in my family; be reconciled to me, and I wil be reconciled vnto you. My Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Legates, I haue ſent into al quarters to preach my peace vnto you, and offer you pardon. Conſider and ſee; this is al that I your Lord God require at your handes, that ye leaue diſſimulation, that ye loue me, and feare me aboue al, walking before me in a perfect and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right hart. Doe this and liue for euer, ye ſhal be my children and I wil be your Father.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:16437:65"/>
            <lg>
               <l>SHal this Embaſſage be of no regard?</l>
               <l>Sent from a God, and from a man beſides</l>
               <l>Who for thy ſake in loue he hath not ſpard.</l>
               <l>His head, his armes, his legs, his ſacred ſides,</l>
               <l>But al haue beene embrued in deareſt blood,</l>
               <l>To ſaue thy ſoule, and worke thy greateſt good.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Bond-ſlaue thou waſt, to hel and to damnation,</l>
               <l>No worldly meanes from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce could ſet thee fre.</l>
               <l>No price on earth, to ranſome thy ſaluation,</l>
               <l>But what alone muſt be performd by me.</l>
               <l>I ſpared not, what treaſure heauen did hold.</l>
               <l>To gaine for heauen, what to hel was ſold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I tooke mans fleſh, deſcending for thy ſake.</l>
               <l>I paſt to hel, to free thy ſoule from thence.</l>
               <l>What to requite me darſt thou vndertake?</l>
               <l>At what Tribunal pleade in my defence?</l>
               <l>The world doth te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt, thou yeldeſt, deuils threte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</l>
               <l>Betwixt them both, thy Sauiour is forgotten.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou loueſt the world, &amp; therefore loath to loſe it.</l>
               <l>Thou feareſt the power of helliſh damned crue.</l>
               <l>Thy ſoule is mine, and thou durſt not diſpoſe, it.</l>
               <l>Little remembring what thou haſt to rue.</l>
               <l>Wilt thou refuſe me, now the time is thine?</l>
               <l>And then preſume, when that the day is mine?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:16437:66"/>
               <l>Thy time is now thou fighteſt for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> crowne</l>
               <l>I firſt beganne the conflict and the fight.</l>
               <l>I wan the field, and put the Deuils downe.</l>
               <l>I ſhewd leſſe way, how thou might gaine thy right,</l>
               <l>Mercy is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, whilſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> life doth laſt.</l>
               <l>Iuſtice do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> follow, when this date is paſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let loue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> flame thee, firſt for thy creation,</l>
               <l>Thou a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not able to content me truly.</l>
               <l>Then what thou oweſt for thy wrought ſaluation,</l>
               <l>Is not in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce to make requital duly.</l>
               <l>Yeeld loue for loue, let not thy loue be plaſt</l>
               <l>Where loue turnes hate, when that this lif is paſt,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What loue, what terrour, al the world may yeeld,</l>
               <l>Al are but ſhadowes, glaunſing on a wal,</l>
               <l>Or like the winde, ſtowping the corne in field,</l>
               <l>They haue ſhort ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, of no regard at al.</l>
               <l>The loue of heauen the dreadful judgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Theſe, theſe, are they, whoſe end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>not decay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Chooſe now of whether thou wilt haue thy ſhare.</l>
               <l>Of that, which endeth in a moments blaſt.</l>
               <l>Or of thoſe treaſures, which I doe prepare,</l>
               <l>For my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> which ſhal euer laſt.</l>
               <l>The world is go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy Sauiour ſhal rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine.</l>
               <l>Stand la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and heauen is thy gaine</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
